<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A cluster of sweetest grapes for saints, brought from the heavenly Canaan. Or, The saints assurance gotten, and to be had in this life, by the several means specified in this tract upon I Pet. 1.9. And fifteen soul-solacing conferences with Christ, touching sins and the world's conquest; according to the high and noble art of fighting the great fight of Faith, I Tim.6.12. Fitted for all such gracious souls as do most heartily desire to see the death of their strong and mighty corruptions, &amp; a thorow [sic] victory gotten over this vile and troublesome world. By Christopher Jelinger M. A.</title>
            <author>Jelinger, Christopher.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 220 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 118 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46733</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J541</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217025</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828727</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828727</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33158</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46733)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33158)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1967:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A cluster of sweetest grapes for saints, brought from the heavenly Canaan. Or, The saints assurance gotten, and to be had in this life, by the several means specified in this tract upon I Pet. 1.9. And fifteen soul-solacing conferences with Christ, touching sins and the world's conquest; according to the high and noble art of fighting the great fight of Faith, I Tim.6.12. Fitted for all such gracious souls as do most heartily desire to see the death of their strong and mighty corruptions, &amp; a thorow [sic] victory gotten over this vile and troublesome world. By Christopher Jelinger M. A.</title>
                  <author>Jelinger, Christopher.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 145, 156-226 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year 1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Text is continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>"Fifteen soul-solacing conferences with Christ," has separate dated title page; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Spiritual life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33158:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A Cluſter of ſweeteſt GRAPES FOR SAINTS, Brought from the <hi>Heavenly Canaan.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>OR, The Saints Aſſurance, gotten, and to be had in this Life, by the ſeveral means ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified in this Tract upon
<bibl>1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.9.</bibl>
                  </p>
                  <p>And fifteen Soul-ſolacing Conferences with Chriſt, touching Sins and the World's Conqueſt; according to the high and noble Art of fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the great fight of Faith,
<bibl>1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.12.</bibl>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fitted for all ſuch gracious Souls as do moſt heartily deſire to ſee the death of their ſtrong and mighty corruptions, &amp; a thorow victory gotten over this vile and troubleſome World.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>Christopher Jelinger</hi> M. A.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the year 1664.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:33158:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:33158:2"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:33158:3"/>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33158:3"/>
                  <head>Epigramma Authoris Auſpicatorium, ad JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M CHRIST<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M, REGEM REG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M, Dominum ſuum Clementiſſimum.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>CHriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Decus Coeli, Coelorum Gloria, Chriſte,</l>
                     <l>Unica Progenies ex Deitate Patris,</l>
                     <l>Adveniat nobis Regnum, quod nomine Coeli</l>
                     <l>Scripturae dicunt, adveniatque ſalus:</l>
                     <l>Monſtretur nobis facies tua, Maxime Regum,</l>
                     <l>Et tendat ſurſum quicquid ad ima ruit;</l>
                     <l>Adveniat quo<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> laeta Canan, quae dulcia ſemper</l>
                     <l>Tundit mella probis angeliciſque viris,</l>
                     <l>Tempora decedant, quibus (heu) FIDUCIA nobi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Defuit, &amp; veniant tempora grata Tuis;</l>
                     <l>Adveniat nova Lux, veniant Saturnia Saec'la</l>
                     <l>Quae exhilarent Sanctos, Optime Chriſte, tuos<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Accedatque piis FIDUCIA Magna ſalutis,</l>
                     <l>Et guſtent Juſti gaudia, magna Poli,</l>
                     <l>Adveniat cunctis etiam, ſperantibus in te</l>
                     <l>Fons vitae, ſemper dulcibus Uber aquis;</l>
                     <l>Ambroſios libent Coeleſti è Nectare Rores</l>
                     <l>Qui Coelum ſitiunt, juſtitiamque Dei;</l>
                     <l>Adveniat porro Coeleſtis Muſica, Chriſte,</l>
                     <l>Et nos nunc recreent Jubila Grata Poli,</l>
                     <l>Quae nec Julaeae voces, nec tibia poſſit.</l>
                     <l>Muſica Cyrrhaeis aſſimilare Modis,</l>
                     <l>Et te collaudent, ſpes, O fidiſſima Mundi,</l>
                     <l>Omnia quae exiſtunt, Lux, Polus, arva, fretum</l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33158:4"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:33158:4"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>To the truly Vertuous Lady, the Lady</hi> Margaret Courtney, <hi>Grace &amp; Peace from God the Father, and from the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>MADAM,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
                     </hi> Cannot but be mindful of you alſo in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Treatiſes.</p>
                  <p>Your gracious carriage and good report which you have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong good and gracious peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;
<pb facs="tcp:33158:5"/>and your exemplary for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs to come to our Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures when they were up; and the great reſpect which I have, and fervent love which I bear to your Noble Family, ſince I came firſt acquainted with it, hath in a manner conſtrained me ſo to do, and by name to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate unto you theſe <hi>Soul-ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacing Conferences with Chriſt</hi> which I have penn'd, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earneſt requeſt of others publiſhed, for the good of all ſuch gracious ſouls as do deſire no better talk than ſuch as is contained in one of theſe Books, and doubtleſs is moſt pleaſing to Chriſt. Chriſt you know did ſoon draw near to
<pb facs="tcp:33158:5"/>thoſe
<note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 24.15.</note> 
                     <hi>Emauntiſh</hi> Pilgrims, who did but talk of him; and therefore much more will not be far from us alſo, if we ſhall not only talk ſo of him, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo with him; eſpecially when he ſhall ſee that we do moſt heartily deſire to ſee the death of our ſins, and to live above this vile and evil world, as Conqueror of it, and not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered by it. Oh! that doth his very heart good; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore how? Oh how ſhould we confer and talk, and commune with him about it even day and night, that we may oppoſe it with all our might, proſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and prevailing againſt it to our ſouls delight?</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:33158:6"/>
                  <p>Madam, Chriſt will be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding glad of our talk, if we ſhall ſo talk with him, as here we are taught of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of this world, that we may reign with him in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther world.</p>
                  <p>His heavenly Highneſs therefore gives us hearts to ſpeak as we ought to ſpeak, that after we have ſpoken with him here, we may be ſpoken unto, by him hereafter, to triumph with him for ever.</p>
                  <closer>So prayeth 
<signed>Your moſt humble ſervant in Chriſt Chriſtopher Jelinger.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33158:6"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>To the Worſhipful</hi> THOMAS REYNEL, <hi>
                        <abbr>Eſq</abbr> And Juſtice of the Peace, Grace and Mercy be multiplyed</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>WORSHIPF<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>L,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Aay it pleaſe you to give me leave to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate, and to preſent this little Tract of <hi>The Saints Aſſurance</hi> unto you, as to a Perſon ſo enobled with Grace, as that by God's Grace enabling you, I hope you wil not only Patronize it; but alſo promote my grand deſign in it, which is to ſtir up all that ſhall read it, to the gaining of the ſaid
<pb facs="tcp:33158:7"/>Aſſurance thorow Gods aſſiſtance.</p>
                  <p>Worthy Sir, you ſee what a Subject I am faln upon, even a Subject which will ſubject our fears, eject our doubts, and deject all adverſe powers, which in the want of this Aſſurance are wont illaqueate our very intellects, to captivate our wills, and to ſubju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate all the powers of our ſouls. Souls therefore will never do well till they be heavened with it; for my part, when I take a full circle of my ſelf, and a thorow view of my condition, do find without it my very being to be a burden, my life a
<note n="*" place="margin">Suſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the loſs of the light of God's counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</note> loſs, my heart a hell; for Oh the hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh horrors that a man ſhall feel in his heart, when this Aſſurance is far from his heart! But when
<pb facs="tcp:33158:7"/>it is in it, O what a glad man is he! Heaven being in his heart, his heart in Heaven; Oh Sir! what a Heaven, what a Paradiſe, what a beatitude did circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe that holy * Father, when,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>St.</hi> Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom.</note> as he writes of himſelf, he was, as it were, <hi>in medio Angelorum choro,</hi> in the very midſt of the quire of Angels, hearing them ſing, as he was <hi>in Eremo,</hi> in a Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs! and may not we be ſo too? yes verily, if we would but labour, as we ought, for this Aſſurance, treading into the Veſtigaes or footſteps of thoſe bleſſed Hebrews, who were ſo aſſured of their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and eternal bliſs, according to that memorable expreſſion of the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb. 10.34. Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:33158:8"/>(mark) <hi>knowing in your ſelvs, that you have in Heaven a better and more enduring ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance;</hi> for then as they thereby were, ſo we thereby ſhall come to the innumerable company of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, &amp;c. <hi>Heb. 12.22.</hi> Confeſs I muſt that it is as hard a thing to acquire, and to gain this Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, as any thing I know in the world, and you know, Sir, how the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth fulmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and thunder out her
<note n="*" place="margin">Council. Trid. ſeſs. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi> &amp; <hi>16.</hi>
                     </note> Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema's againſt us, for maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Aſſurance to be had in this life; but I am not diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from this treating on it by ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for againſt the one, I know that I am defenſated and born up by God's never-failing Truth, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb facs="tcp:33158:8"/>the other by his power; and therefore I ſay, for all this, let us, O let us labour, and labour hard (becauſe our work is ſo hard) &amp; ſtrive, as for life, to be perſwaded in our hearts, that without fail and doubt we ſhall enter into life. Life here is ſweet, but that above is ſweeter, &amp; the Aſſurance of it the ſweeteſt thing in all this world's circumference; for when a man hath it, he may truly ſay of it, Oh! what a life do I now live, living by the faith of the Son of God
<note n="*" place="margin">Gal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2.20.</note> who loved me and gave himſelf for me? Oh the unexpreſſible peace which I now have within me, being perſwaded in my breaſt that with heavenly bliſs I ſhall be for ever bleſt! Oh what a glorying
<pb facs="tcp:33158:9"/>joy doth now warm me! what a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Ocean of comfort overflow me and what a Heaven of glory becir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle me! Oh this Aſſurance, this heavenly Aſſurance <hi>is nothing elſe but the very gate of Heaven,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid once of the place where he ſaw the Angels of God aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and deſcending upon a Ladder which reached to Heaven, <hi>Gen. 27.17.</hi> Oh Sir, could we but fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thoſe leſſons which are laid down for our going up as it were by ſteps to that height of hope, which in this life a man may tower up to; could we live ſuch a ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, ſuch a ſtrict, ſuch an holy, ſuch a ſeraphical life as here is ſhewn us, could we get the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of our ſins ſealed to us, could
<pb facs="tcp:33158:9"/>we gain that high and unqueſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable teſtimony of Gods holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which is to be had by us, how ſoon would this be our caſe too? and how ſoon would we be able to eccho forth the ſame expeſſions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing filled with unparallelable conſolations? Oh Sir, let us ſtir therefore, and ſtrive to our utmoſt, to expreſs the vertue, the life, the power of the things here ſhewn us, labouring eſpecially for a guſt of the very joys of Heaven, which here we are pointed to; and to lead an extraordinary, exemplary, blameleſs, moſt holy, and heavenly life, which we are appointed to: And what I ſay to your worthy ſelf, and my unworthy ſelf, I ſay to all; ſtrive, Oh ſtrive with all
<pb facs="tcp:33158:10"/>your might, for this moſt glorious and Heavenly Aſſurance of your ſalvation, which you expect to an endleſs duration for your ſouls delight.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Worſhips moſt humble Servant, Chriſtopher Jelinger.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33158:10"/>
                  <head>A CLUSTER OF Sweeteſt Grapes for Saints Newly brought from the Heavenly <hi>Canaan.</hi> OR, The Saints Aſſurance, Upon 1 PET. 1.9. <hi>Even the Salvation of your Souls.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Soul longs, and loveth to be there where ſhe may be happy, and ſo ſhe looks upon this Text as a Theme, whoſe handling and following (with God's bleſſing) is able to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33158:11"/>centre her ſo, as that ſhe ſhall be bleſſed; for it carrieth happineſs in its boſom, and is ready to bring Salvation, and the Aſſurance of it to it, and to every believing Saint, who carries Chriſt in his heart: ſo that for this very end I have choſen it, that thereby I may unload my fraighted mind, and purſue my much drawn forth, and (for the Saints Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of their ſalvation) bound and bent intention. If we look a little higher we ſhall ſee a very heap of Bleſſings cumulated and laid together by bleſſed <hi>Peter,</hi> as ſtreaming from the Fountain of all bleſſings, to wit, God's infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, and not to be fathomed mercy, <hi>v.</hi> 3.</p>
                  <p>More particularly he enume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates theſe following mercies:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Regeneration, <hi>v.</hi> 3. Then</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Glorification, <hi>v.</hi> 4. And</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Perſeverance, by the power
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33158:11"/>of God here to be enjoyed, <hi>v.</hi> 5. Then</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Onſpeakable joy already obtained, <hi>v.</hi> 6.</p>
                  <p>Which done, he ſuperadds the procreant cauſe of the ſaid great and glorious joy, as namely, a moſt certain hope of eternal life in my Text, <hi>Even the ſalvation of your ſouls.</hi> Where, let us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider,
<note n="2" place="margin">Parts of the Text.</note>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. <hi>What.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>Whoſe.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>What. Even the ſalvation,
<note n="1" place="margin">Part</note> which cometh in thus,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Receiving,</hi> which neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily infers a great Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</note> Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the end of your Faith,</hi>
                     <note n="†" place="margin">Gagneius in Loc. per Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton. Adj. Haebr.</note> or <hi>fruit,</hi> as ſome, by your unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able joy, <hi>v.</hi> 8. and then by way of Amplification, <hi>Even the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, &amp;c. Salvation</hi> is taken,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. For an external Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.13.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. For the
<note n="‖" place="margin">Metonymice.</note> Author of any ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 27.1.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Chriſt eſpecially the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33158:12"/>of our ſalvation, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.30.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Our ſpiritual deliverance in the beginning of our converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.9.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Our eternal deliverance from Sin and Satan and everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing happineſs, conſiſting of two degrees.</p>
                  <p>The firſt is enjoyed, when be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unmanned by death, we are carried in the arms of Angels, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the arms of Chriſt who is the head of Angels, as <hi>Luke</hi> 16.22.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond will be enjoyed after judgment, when being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuſcitated out of the duſt of the earth, we ſhall be enroabed with the refulgent beams of ſparkling glory, in the Kingdom of glory, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.14.
<note place="margin">Tropic.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. The ſure and certain
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Spes eſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dubitatus ante theſaurum the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaurus,</hi> Joh. Clim. <hi>gr.</hi> 30.</note> hope of ever during bliſs, and never fading glory in the foretaſt of it, as here, where I find ſome Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitors ſo to underſtand this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33158:12"/>Scripture; I for my part, took this to be the ſenſe of this high and lofty place, before I ſaw what others ſay; but when I found others to be of the ſame mind, I was glad and mightily corroborated in my judgment. I will cite at preſent, but one paſſage out of
<note place="margin">Piſcator in Loc.</note> one, who wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting upon this Text, <hi>Even the ſalvation of your ſouls;</hi> ſaith thus, that is the certain hope of eternal life, in that they did moſt certainly hope that they ſhould obtain ſalvation, as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of Faith; thus he: but I do moſt of all ground this Expoſition upon <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.24. For we <hi>are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by hope,</hi> that is, we are aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by an undoubted and a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain hope, that we ſhall be ſaved. For otherwiſe we are not alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſaved, but ſhall be, a notable place for our
<note place="margin">But if any will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, yet will he be forced to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of this by me here un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood <hi>Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> by the foregoing word <hi>Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving,</hi> for wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> we receive we are ſure of.</note> purpoſe and this Aſſurance. The Greek word for
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33158:13"/>ſalvation here is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> from <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, which ſignifies, I defend, and preſerve; and ſo it ſhews how when ſalvation comes, defence comes; and preſervation comes. For when it comes, we come to be defended againſt and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from all the evils which now we feel, or fear, and eſpecially, Death and Damnation, by a great and glorious deliverance.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Whoſe.
<note n="2" place="margin">Part.</note> 
                     <hi>Your ſouls.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Souls.</hi> And yet hath each man but one,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Videatur</hi> Suaretz <hi>Diſput. Suet. to.</hi> 2. <hi>dep.</hi> 15. Sect. 8.</note> not two, as ſome have held. For God breathed into <hi>Adam</hi> the breath of life, (that is, a rational Soul) not breaths, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.7.</p>
                  <p>But what is a Soul?</p>
                  <p>It is an Act, ſaith the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, of a body
<note n="*" place="margin">Ariſt. l. 2. <hi>de Anim<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cui aſſentit Suaretz Met. Diſp. to.</hi> 1. <hi>Diſp. is S. W</hi> 8.</note> organical, which hath life
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Religio me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dici,</hi> p. 79.</note> potentially, in it ſelf being inorganical; mark, inorga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical, for the Learned in Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my tells us, that among thoſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33158:13"/>rare diſcoveries, and curious pieces they obſerve in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick of man, they find no Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, or inſtrument for the ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Soul of man; for in the brain, which we tearm the ſeat of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, there is not any thing more of moment, than there is in the Crany of a Beaſt: thus we ſpeak according to Philoſophers, as far as they are agreed, for they do not all, nor can agree among themſelves, ſo as to tell us exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what it is. But what ſaith Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity of it?</p>
                  <p>I Anſw. That it is a ſpirit,
<note n="*" place="margin">Lactant. 1. <hi>de Opif. Dei,</hi> c. 17.</note> and breath of life, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.9. If you go farther, and ask me, But what is that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and that breath of life? I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, It is ſomething in us, and in
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſt tota in toto corpore, &amp; in qualibe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> parte ejus,</hi> Petr. Lomb. c. 8. l. 1. <hi>Et non in cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> de tantum, ut ſcribit,</hi> Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. l. 3. <hi>de Anim.</hi> c. 15.</note> every part of us; but can be without us, and will be after us; though it be hardly known how it came into us; and how ſeated
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33158:14"/>in us, bleſſed <hi>Auſtin</hi> ingeniouſly confeſſeth it that he cannot tell, or thus, it is a truly ſpiritual Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence;
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Num ſit ex raduce, vel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>reata, ut nos <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>enſemus cum</hi> Lactant. <hi>de Opif. Dei,</hi> c. 19. <hi>&amp; aliis. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> Bucan.</hi> l. 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 115.</note> incorporeal, immaterial, and ſubſiſting; when it is ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the body.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Your Souls,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Contra Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ull. qui eam definet eſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>orproream,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 3. <hi>de Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>a, c.</hi> 7.</note> meaning the Souls of Saints, <hi>v.</hi> 8. who belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and rejoycing in Chriſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the end of their Faith, which is the certainty of their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, which cometh by Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Whence note.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                     </label> That
<note n="*" place="margin">If any would have this Doct. to run thus, That <hi>Saints</hi> in this life may gain and have this Aſſurance, he may take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>it ſo. But I, to encourage all Men to labor for it, ſhall uſe here the word <hi>Men,</hi> and yet chiefly aim at Saints.</note> men in this life may gain and have the Aſſurance of their Souls ſalvation. See <hi>Job.</hi> 9.27. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22.34. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.78. and eſpecially <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.14.</p>
                  <p>Where give me leave to ſhew,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. What this Aſſurance is.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Why men in this life may gain it.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. What it is, namely, The ſoul of Faith, the Paradiſe of Saints, the <hi>Canaan</hi> of Believers,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33158:14"/>the Ladder of Life, the Life of Heaven. Or thus, it is that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we re-enter Paradiſe, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount all ordinary men, triumph over hell, tranſcend our ſelves, and aſcend into Heaven it ſelf. See <hi>Calvin. Inſt. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>Sect.</hi> 16. how he defines it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Why Men in this life may gain and have it.</p>
                  <p>As Namely, 1. By reaſon of,
<note n="1" place="margin">Reaſon.</note> faith
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Fidem ipſam quiſque videt in corde ſuo, ſi credit</hi> Auguſtinus. <hi>Cui aſſentit</hi> Petr. Lomb. <hi>diſt.</hi> 23. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>fol.</hi> 259.</note> ſure of their faith, and ſee it, if they have true faith, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12. <hi>I know, whom I have believed;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they may be ſure, alſo that they ſhall be ſaved; for, <hi>He that believeth, and is baptiſed ſhall be ſaved,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. ſee alſo <hi>John</hi> 3.36. and note it well: So that the Apoſtle might well call faith an evidence <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1. and
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde</hi> Baſil <hi>de vera &amp; pia fide,</hi> p. 345. <hi>Eſt approbatio ſine ulla haeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatione cum ſumma per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſione.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Baſil</hi> a moſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>high
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33158:15"/>and undoubted perſwaſion, according to, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.21.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Men may be ſure of their Vocation in this life,
<note n="2" place="margin">Rerſon.</note> if they be called, For <hi>you ſee your calling,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.26. mark, you ſee it, as a man may ſee himſelf to be out of a peſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, out of a priſon, out of darkneſs, ſo a man may ſee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf called out of the peſt-houſe and priſon of ſin, and out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs brought into God's marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous light. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it followeth, that a man may alſo be aſſured that he ſhall be ſaved; For <hi>whom he calleth he glorifieth, Rom.</hi> 8.30.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Men may be ſure of their election by the uſe of means,
<note n="3" place="margin">Reaſon.</note> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſome of the
<note n="‖" place="margin">
                        <hi>Error Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtini de cor. &amp; grat. c.</hi> 3.</note> Ancients denie it, it is evident from, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5, 6. and if ſo, they may be of their ſalvation too; for <hi>whom he did
<note n="†" place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30.</note> prediſtinate, he alſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified;</hi>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:33158:15"/>and if choſen, then chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Having prediſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated us to the adoption of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; and if children, then heirs, Rom.</hi> 8.16. For who ſhall have what we have, but our children? ſo, who ſhall have what God hath, <hi>viz.</hi> life and Heaven, but his Children?</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Men may be ſure of their juſtification, if juſtified,
<note n="4" place="margin">Reaſon.</note>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Hoc nega<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> concil. Trid. Seſſ.</hi> 6. c. 9. <hi>ſed temere. Quid aliud peccata noſtra tegere potuit quam Chriſti juſtitia.</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin Martyr <hi>Epiſt: ad Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ognetum.</hi>
                     </note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by their ſins are forgiven, and covered with Chriſt's Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.5. <hi>Thou forgaveſt the iniquity of my ſin. Selah.</hi> Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, <hi>For whom he juſtified them he alſo glorified,</hi> Rom. 8.30.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Men may be ſure of their ſanctification, if ſanctified;
<note n="5" place="margin">Reaſon.</note> For to be ſanctified, is to ſhine as a light in the dark, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.15. Now, a light in darkneſs muſt needs be ſeen, ſo as that a man may truly ſay, here is light, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon it followeth, that when a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33158:16"/>man ſeeth that he is light in the Lord, and ſhines as a light, he may alſo be aſſured, that he ſhall be ſaved by the Lord, ſee a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13. how therefore ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification and ſalvation are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>link'd together.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Men may be ſure here of their
<note n="6" place="margin">Reaſon.</note>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Videatur Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pr.</hi> p. 141.</note> perſeverance, and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> God's conſtant love to them in Chriſt, if once they be in Chriſt, let the Papiſts deny it a thouſand times, after the tradition of their Fathers; who
<note n="‖" place="margin">
                        <hi>Cyril. Alex.</hi> in <hi>John</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 703. <hi>intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligit noſtram charitatem; &amp; dicit fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les nunquam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>b ea deficere.</hi>
                     </note> Anathematize us for ſaying ſo; It is clear from, <hi>John</hi> 13.1. and from <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.31. <hi>Who ſhall ſeparate us from the love of Chriſt?</hi> and v. 37, 38. <hi>I am perſwaded that neither life, nor death,</hi> &amp;c. Read that famous place. † <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> and <hi>Staple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Rome's</hi> great Champions would have this place to yeild, but only a
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Stapleton Antid. p.</hi> 503.</note> moral, and
<note n="‖" place="margin">
                        <hi>Bellarmine l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>de juſtificatione.</hi>
                     </note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectural certitude, but how can
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Concil. Trid. Seſſ.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 116.</note>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:33158:16"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hey prove it, ſith the Apoſtle ſaith expreſſely; I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of it; they have a ſhift, that <hi>Paul</hi> was perſwaded by a Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ation, which we have not, and that he ſpeaks of
<note n="‖" place="margin">Stapl. ibid.</note> himſelf, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot us; but what ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> when he comes to his Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; he tels us, they were of things not lawful for a man to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>utter, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4. but this he doth utter. <hi>Ergo,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Beſides, he doth not only ſpeak of himſelf, but us alſo; as his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry words ſhew, who ſhall ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate <hi>us?</hi> Mark, <hi>us,</hi> not we. See alſo, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.40. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.29. <hi>John</hi> 10.28. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. For the Saints perſeverance, and compare all with <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.13. <hi>He that ſhall endure unto the end, the ſame ſhall be ſaved.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Now all theſe 7 Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons will ſerve for <hi>Saints</hi> alſo, if you leave out <hi>if ſtill</hi> and that which goeth with it, and put in <hi>Saints</hi> for <hi>Men.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <note n="7" place="margin">Reaſon.</note> Men in this life may feel the joys of Heaven, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon my Text infers; that then
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33158:17"/>they receive the ſalvation of their ſouls; that is, the certain hope of their ſalvation, being already rapt up into Heaven; heavened in glory; emboſomed in God, &amp; elevated to the higheſt zenith of divine conſolation.</p>
                  <p>Now to the Application of this grand Concluſion.
<note place="margin">Uſe of Conſut.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>And firſt, May not this ſerve to confute the Doctrine of the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Concel. Trid. Seſſ.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.</note> Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> averring that no man can in this life be ſure of his juſtification (and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſalvation) without a Revelation.</p>
                  <p>The Champions of that Church, ſtand chiefly upon theſe two Objections, or places of ſcripture which Ile therefore briefly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That,
<note n="1" place="margin">Object.</note> in <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.1. <hi>No man knoweth love, or hatred, by all things before him;</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwered. </seg>
                     </label> To this I anſwer 2 wayes.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:33158:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p n="1">1. That which followes, v. 2. ſhewes the meaning of this place; that no man knoweth that by theſe outward things, and by the event of things.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The words <hi>love</hi> and <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred,</hi> are Metonymically ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered; and expounded by
<note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>Jun.</hi> or <hi>Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel. juxta, v.</hi> 8.</note> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitors; to be things loved; and hated.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The other place is that in <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4, 5. <hi>For it is impoſſible for thoſe that were once enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened,</hi> &amp;c. Read the place. From whence they infer; that a man may go very far; and yet fall away at laſt; and if ſo, how can any man be ſure of ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſeeing he may fall away, though he be never ſo eminent now for holineſs before he dieth?</p>
                  <p>To this I anſwer thus.</p>
                  <p>Either the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of real, or of ſeeming Saints; if of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33158:18"/>real, as ſome would have it; then theſe words, <hi>if they fall away,</hi> muſt be underſtood, as ſpoken by way of ſuppoſition. As 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. <hi>ult.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.1, 2, 3. and <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Though I</hi> (or if as v. 9.) <hi>we, or an Angel from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, preach any other Goſpel un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, than that which we have preached unto you; let him be accurſed.</hi> If, of ſeeming Saints, as I take it, then theſe words, <hi>were once enlightened,</hi> &amp;c. muſt be underſtood of grace <hi>tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliter,</hi> as Divines ſpeak, or for a time received; and of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon work of God's Spirit; and common gifts which Reprobates, and Temporaries, and ſuch as ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt (which ſin, ſome ſay, the Apoſtle here ſpeaks of) may partake of, ſo that, no wonder it is, if they fall away.</p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:33158:18"/>
                  <p n="2">2. But ſecondly,
<note n="2" place="margin">Uſe of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dubitation.</note> may not this afford me matter of Addubita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion alſo? as thus; What ſhall I think then of thoſe, who being Proteſtants do think that they cannot poſſibly be aſſured of their ſalvation in this life; and therefore alwaies doubt and reſt ſo contented? There was a ſect of men once called Skepticks, becauſe they queſtioned every thing, and I take theſe men to be partly of that ſect too, (for ſects do not periſh with their Authors altogether, but like the River <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rethuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> though they loſe their current in one place, they riſe up again in another) but oh the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable infidelity in men pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing Chriſtianity!</p>
                  <p n="3">3. And may not this Doctrine afford us matter of Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion too? Yes verily, as thus;
<note n="3" place="margin">Uſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication. <hi>Addubitati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> eſt deliberati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> nobiſcum Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municatio cum aliis.</hi>
                     </note> Then why do not men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men labour for this Aſſurance; I
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:33158:19"/>ſay this Aſſurance which here I treat of, ſome Aſſurance ſome have, but it is that which is call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Confidence in the fleſh, or Carnal, not this. This not one of a thouſand hath, nor ſeeks after. But why? my Brethren why? ſhall I tell you my thoughts, ſome do not, becauſe they are not will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to go to the pains which this Aſſurance coſts him that will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it, and herein even ſome true Believers may be faulty. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers do believe that they do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, when they do not, and ſo do not labour after Faith, nor Aſſurance, for why ſhould they labour after it, ſay they, ſeeing they have it already? when either they have no Faith at all, or if any but a Dogmatical, or Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary, which is but a deceitful Faith like <hi>Alcumi.</hi> The <hi>Alcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts</hi> are grown to that ſkill, that they will make <hi>Alcumi</hi> appear
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33158:19"/>to be perfect Silver and Gold, &amp; much of it will bear the touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, that one can hardly diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it, but when fire and hammer come to it, it will bear neither of them, for it comes not from the right place whence Gold and Silver comes, namely from mines; ſo men are come up to that height of ſkill in deceiving that they will deceive any, for they will make their Temporary Faith e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to gliſten like Gold, and it will paſs for true Faith amongſt men; and for a time hold even under ſome tryals, but when greater tribulations indeed come and the word like fire and a ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer comes, their Faith is diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to be no true ſaving Faith, for it cannot endure either, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it came not the right way, whence true faith comes, namely by the Word, and by true, and ſound, and deep humiliation;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33158:20"/>and there is much of that <hi>Alcumi.</hi> Faith now going, &amp; that is much the cauſe of it why men want this Aſſurance, but I wonder how ſome of you, who are under this want, can be ſo contented; if a woman have a husband that can aſſure her of ſomething, ſhe will be aſſured of ſomething, or elſe ſhe will not be contented, nor let him to be quiet; and if a man have but one child, he will do what he can to make it aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of ſomething after his death, and till then he will not reſt; but you methinks can reſt, and ſit ſtill, and be contented, though you be certain of nothing; that is, though you be nothing at all aſſured, as ye ought to be, of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bliſs or bleſſedneſs that you ſhall have hereafter in Heaven, and though you have but one poor ſoul each of you to be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and provided for, &amp; though
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33158:20"/>you know that God, who is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Husband to ſome of you, is able to aſſure you of ſomething indeed, I mean of Heaven and happineſs for ever, O monſtrous careleſneſs! O ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious ſecurity! O how can you chuſe but even doubt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you have any
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Nam vere fiddis non eſt niſi qui divina benevolentiae promiſſionibus fretus indubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatam ſalutis expectationem praeſumit,</hi> Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin <hi>Inſt. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2. ſ. 10.</note> true faith at all yea or no, it being a <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or
<note n="*" place="margin">Though wreſtling with doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings which oppoſe it and by degrees are overcome by it.</note> full perſwaſion? <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. I come next to a Uſe of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citation, to ſtir up my ſelf &amp; you to labour therefore for this Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance;
<note n="4" place="margin">Uſe of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citation.</note> ſeeing it is ſo to be had in this life. For the better ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging of which Uſe I ſhall ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to you.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Directives,</hi> or <hi>Mediums.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Incentives.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Directives,</hi> to wit, theſe.
<note n="1" place="margin">Directives.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Labour to be born again if ye are not,
<note n="1" place="margin">Direct.</note> for ſo were thoſe bleſſed Saints here; who were ſo aſſured of their ſalvation, as
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33158:21"/>you may ſee v. 3. <hi>Hath begotten us again.</hi> Give me leave there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to inſiſt upon Regeneration a little while. And</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Let me intrat you to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bibe, receive, and take inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the word of Regeneration; whereby we are born again; as it is written, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23. <hi>Being born again, not of corruptible ſeed, but of incorruptible, by the word of God, which liveth and abideth for ever,</hi> where note, that this Regenerating word of God is partly Law &amp; partly Goſpel.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. As Law, and ſo it doth three things.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. It diſcovereth unregenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and unregenerate men, and ſhewes what manner of men they are like a glaſs, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.23. as for example, by that famous place, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>m.</hi> 3.10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18. where it deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth them, what throats, mouths,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:33158:21"/>tongues, feet, they have, I pray you read the place. It is ſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of <hi>Luther,</hi> that a certain <hi>Jew</hi> would have poyſoned him, but was diſcovered by his picture, ſent to <hi>Luther,</hi> by a faithful friend, warning him to beware of ſuch a man, when he did ſee him, ſuch a faithful friend is the law which ſo diſcovers unregenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, which would kill us, by ſuch a portracture that we may eſcape it, and live.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It puts life into ſin, as you may read, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.8, 9. <hi>I was alive without the law once; but when the commandement came, ſin revived, and I dyed:</hi> this is a notable place, I pray you, let me open it a little, <hi>ſin revived,</hi> that is, it began to ſtir, to tear,
<note place="margin">Nitimur in vetitum ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, cupimuſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> negata.</note> to irrit, to exite, to do what is forbidden; and to affright withall, as ſome underſtand the place ſo that I felt it. Before
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:33158:22"/>the law comes home cloſe; ſin is as it were dead; like a dead adder or Lion, and ſo quiet; but when the law comes, it is like an adder which is alive, ſo it bites, and
<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.56</note> ſtings, and like a living Lion, ſo it roars, and ſo it ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifieth, and makes men afraid to
<note n="‖" place="margin">
                        <hi>Deducit e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim talis me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ad poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam.</hi> Clem. Alex. <hi>ſtrom: l.</hi> 2. p. 58.</note> bring them to repentance, and Regeneration.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It killeth, according to the fore-alledged place, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.9. <hi>Sin revived, and I died;</hi> that is, I felt and ſaw, that I was dead and damned by the law, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as before I was alive; that is, I thought as ſure that I ſhould be ſaved as any man alive. Thus the law kills men, and makes them ſenſible of the miſerable ſad and damnable condition wherein they are, whileſt they are in the ſtate of unregeneracie: according to that dreadful place, <hi>John</hi> 3.3. Read it.</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:33158:22"/>
                  <p n="2">2. As Goſpel, ſo the regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating word of God holds forth one ſweet &amp; precious promiſe or other, like an orient pearl, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive the dying, drooping ſpirits of men when the law hath brought them as it were to deaths door; as for example, That moſt refulgent and reviving pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.26. <hi>And new heart alſo will I give you, and a new ſpirit will I put within you; and I will take away the ſtonie heart out of your fleſh, and I will give you an heart of fleſh.</hi> Thus the Goſpel opens a
<note n="†" place="margin">Hoſ. 2.15.</note> door of hope for poor creatures condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the law; that though they are, and muſt be priſoners, and condemned priſoners, yet they may be priſoners of hope, <hi>Zac.</hi> 9.12. that is, may not be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome hopes of mercy; and of a gracious deliverance,</p>
                  <p>Thus the law kills, but the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33158:23"/>ſaves. The law cometh, bringing Damnation, but the Goſpel comes bringing ſalvation; the law cometh with a dagger to ſtab thoſe that are alive; but the Goſpel cometh with a plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to cure thoſe that are ſtab'd; and lie for dead, as Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf came to ſave thoſe that were loſt; ſo the Goſpel cometh to bring men to Chriſt, that they may not be loſt; for when ſouls come to Chriſt, being born again by the word of Chriſt; Chriſt comes to them, and when he comes, ſalvation comes; for he cometh <hi>bringing Salvation, Zach.</hi> 9.9. (Read the place) that thoſe which were under the ſentence of Damnation, may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to the ſtate of Salvation, <hi>even the Salvation of their ſouls,</hi> according to my text. Now, this regenerating word of God, you muſt take, and apply every
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:33158:23"/>one of you, and not put it off, or let it lie as dead; ſaying; Am not I ſuch an unregenerate man now? have not I ſuch filthy hands, which have touched the unclean thing? Such a throat, ſuch feet, ſuch a mouth, and ſuch a tongue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which hath talked ſo filthily? &amp;c. But yet may not I hope that the Lord will ſhew me mercy, and regenerate me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, as well as others, Giving me a new heart? &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Betake your ſelves to your
<note n="*" place="margin">Matth. 6.6. and I allude to Eſa. 26.20</note> Chamber, and ſpend at leaſt one day as a day of
<note n="‖" place="margin">Jejuniis &amp; orationibus vacato. Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</note> faſting; I have done the ſame upon the ſame account; if you think that the time of your regeneration is near come, as I hope it is, and that the pangs of the new birth are at the door, and ſhut your door, and there, and then ſee your ſelves convert, according to <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.4. thus rendered in your Engliſh meetre.</p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:33158:24"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And in your Chamber quietly</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>See you, your ſelves convert.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <p n="4">4. Begin to be in pain there as a woman in travel, for the pangs of Child-birth muſt go before the Child's-birth, and you muſt make this
<note n="†" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Preſton</hi> on Gods Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuff.</note> account, that if you never yet received the ſpirit of bondage, you alſo never received the ſpirit of Adoption, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15. and many there are, who, becauſe they have withſtood the troubles of their mindes, and the terrors of the ſpirit of bondage, have withſtood their Salvation; wherefore let me intreat you to take the pains, to be in pains for a little ſeaſon, that you may be at eaſe to an endleſs duration, and for a ſmall moment to be in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vineſs, through ſome neceſſary perturbations, that for ever you may be in joy and gladneſs, through unſpeakable conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. O let even all your joy be
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:33158:24"/>turned into ſorrow now, and your
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſto ſicut Rex in corde tuo; ſublimis &amp; riſui jubens vade ut vadat, &amp; dic tu fletui, veni ut veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at. Clim. Grad.</hi> 15.</note> laughter into grief; that all your grief and ſorrow had for ſin now, may be turned into laughter hereafter; <hi>For bleſſed are ye that weep now, for you ſhall laugh,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 6.21.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Then cry out, and</p>
                  <p n="1">1. For Anguiſh.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. For, and to the ſpirit.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. For Anguiſh, as a
<note n="*" place="margin">I allude to that famous place in <hi>Eſa.</hi> 26.17. <hi>Like as a Woman with child, that draweth neer the time of her delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, is in pain and cryeth out in her pangs: ſo have we been in thy ſight, O Lord.</hi>
                     </note> woman when her time is near, and her pangs begin to come upon her, or as a child cryeth as ſoon as it is born, ſo you before you be new born; as thus, what will become of our poor ſouls? for they are yet unregenerate, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot in any wiſe enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kingdom of Heaven, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe extraordinary mercy be ſhewn them by the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; or thus, as the <hi>Egyptians</hi> once cryed out, when there was
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33158:25"/>not an houſe in all <hi>Egypt,</hi> where there was not one dead; ſaying <hi>We be all dead men,</hi> Exod. 12.30, 33. <hi>And there was a great cry in</hi> Egypt <hi>(See the place.)</hi> So let there be a great cry among you in every houſe and family, (For I believe that there is ſcarce an houſe where there is not one or more unregenerate and dead) and in your ſeveral chambers,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which you have, according to my premiſed advice, betaken your ſelves, and let your cry be the ſame that was in <hi>Egypt. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> we are all dead men;</hi> we that are unregenerate men, for the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it, That <hi>except a man be born again, he cannot ſee the Kingdom of God, John</hi> 3.3. Not all the art and wit of man, Not all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orick of the eloquent'ſt Orator, Not all the in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ies of Saints and Angels can therefore, or will perſwade
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33158:25"/>God to take one that is a drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, or Whoremaſter, or Uſurer, or Lyar, or Thief, or covetous man (and ſuch have been ſome of us) into his Kingdom,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> even as not all the perſwaſions of the men of this Country are or will be able to prevail with any one of us, to take but one toad, or ſnake into his boſome. Thus cry out for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Cry out for, and to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Regeneration, for by the ſpirit alſo a man muſt be born a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, according to that famous ſaying of our Saviour, <hi>John</hi> 3.5. where note that the Spirit doth three things to regenerate ſouls.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. He convinceth them, <hi>John</hi> 16.8, 9.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He injects the feed of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation into them, according to that of Saint <hi>John, His ſeed remains in them,</hi> 1 John 3.9.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. He delivers them and makes
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:33158:26"/>them free, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.17. helping them to come forth out of the dark womb of nature, into his marvelous light, that by him as by a
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Irenaeus adv. haereſ. bal.</hi> l. 3. c. 40.</note> Ladder they may aſcend into
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>John</hi> 3.35.</note> Heaven to our Father which is in Heaven; ſo that unto him you muſt cry and ſay, O bleſſed ſpirit of Regeneration, Regenerate our ſouls, O our poor ſouls that they may live, O con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince them of their unregenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; O inject the feed of Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration into them from above; Oh help them to come forth; Oh let a new heart be given to us, O let us have flexible, and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hearts, like the heart of a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle child; for we alſo muſt be like little children; Oh come bleſſed ſpirit, come and help us, Oh come quickly, come preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and deliver us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> come now whileſt we are in this Room, waiting for thee, as thou comeſt
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:33158:26"/>upon the Apoſtles in that houſe wherein they were ſitting, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.2, 3. O, let this be the time of our regeneration, that we alſo may be ſure of our Salvation: here be earneſt, and cry mightily; Nay, if need be, and thou canſt not be heard in that day, cry in the night too; and ſo come to the Spirit at this time, as <hi>Nicode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> came to Chriſt in old time; even by night, and ſo cry day and night; and then it will not be long before thou ſhalt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, being regenerated; for as Chriſt ſaid once, <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.7, 8. <hi>And ſhall not God hear his elect, which cry unto him day and night; though he bear long with them? I tell you that he will avenge them ſpeedily.</hi> So I, ſhall not the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God hear his elect which cry unto him day and night? I tell you that he will hear them, and deliver them ſpeedily; <hi>For ask,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:33158:27"/>and you ſhall have</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.9. It is no more but aſk and have; aſk therefore the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and you ſhall have
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>How much more ſhall your heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther give the Holy Spirit to them that ask him.</hi> Luke 11.13.</note> him; aſk Regeneration of the ſpirit (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand in the manner afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid) and you ſhall have it, and it will not be long before you ſhall hear the ſpirit cry <hi>Abba Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15.</note> even moſt emphatically; For, therefore to the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Abba</hi> from the Hebrew <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Jun. &amp; Tremel. in Marc.</hi> 14.14.</note> 
                     <hi>Syriack</hi> word <hi>Abba,</hi> is added Father; if you ſhall ſo cry day and night for the ſpirit to the Father, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, there is no crying which the Father of mercies loves bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and the Father of lies likes worſe than this crying, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore uſe it.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Strive to come forth; For as endeavour without God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, ſo God without endeavors will not help us. See <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12, 13. and therefore as Chriſt ſaid once, <hi>ſtrive to enter;</hi> ſo I, ſtrive
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:33158:27"/>to come out, <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.24. for ye will find a very hard bout before ye will be able to come out; therefore I ſay again, ſtrive, and ſtrive as other children do, when they come to their birth, or thus, ſtrive as once
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 38.29.</note> 
                     <hi>Pharez</hi> and <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah</hi> in <hi>Tamars</hi> womb; nay, as <hi>Pharez</hi> ſo ſtrove as that he made a breach, and was therefore cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Pharez</hi> from that breach; ſo do you, make a breach as it were and tear away from Natures womb, and tear away from your beds of eaſe and ſin, and tear a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way eſpecially from your luſts, your pride of life, your vile affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, your violent paſſions, your vain, and filthy converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, your uſury, your atheiſm, polytheiſm, and abominable epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curiſm, and whatſoever elſe is contrary to the holy Law of God, thus ſtrive to come out. I pray you pardon my boldneſs which I
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33158:28"/>took by this digreſſion, which carried me ſo far in this Sea of matter concerning our Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and be pleaſed to impute it unto the vehemency of my love, which made me thus to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get and to loſe my ſelf, that you might not loſe your ſelves, which God in mercy grant.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Labour to believe,
<note n="2" place="margin">Direct. or Medium.</note> for ſo did thoſe holy ones, who accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my Text were ſo aſſured of their ſalvation, <hi>v.</hi> 8. and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, if a man do believe, and be ſure of it that he doth, he muſt needs be aſſured alſo that he ſhall be ſaved; For <hi>ſo God loved the world, that he gave his only begotten Son, that whoſoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth in him ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life, John</hi> 3.16. Mark, He
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Nay, he that believeth on the Son hath everlaſting life.</hi> Joh. 3.36. which much more and plainly demonſtrates, that a believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſoul muſt needs be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of its ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, becauſe it hath it.</note> ſhall have it, ſaith Chriſt, as if he ſhould ſay, he may be ſure of it, for the mouth of truth hath ſpoken it. Believe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:33158:28"/>then in the Lord, you that never did yet, and you may be ſure &amp; certain that your ſhall be ſaved: Here give me leave again to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large my ſelf a little upon this moſt needful Medium, whereby you may gain the aſſurance of your ſalvation; ſhewing how you muſt go to work that you may believe.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Hear a powerful and faith preaching Miniſtery as much and as often as you may; for Faith cometh by hearing, the Word be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like water which brings forth fruit, and eſpecially the fruit of Faith, <hi>Iſa,</hi> 55.10. <hi>John</hi> 8.30.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Calvin Inſt. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>ſ.</hi> 6.</note> 
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.17. ſome Divines do therefore call it the Fountain of Faith.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Be convinced, and labour to be convinced, 1. Of your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief, as he <hi>Mark</hi> 9.23. for there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is partly that ſo many be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve not, becauſe they will not
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:33158:29"/>believe that they believe not; &amp; therefore why ſhould they labor to believe, ſeeing they believe already, ſay they. Beloved, go from houſe to houſe, and aſk, ho, are there any Believers here? and they will be ready to ſtone you, ſaying; What do ye make of us? do ye think that we are Devils, or Infidels? we are Chriſtians, we are Chriſtians, and believe in Chriſt as well as you; and as difficult a taſk it is for a Miniſter to convince men of their unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, as any thing almoſt I know of. A Drunkard, a Fornicator, a paſſionate man, a ſwearer, a Sabbath-breaker, he may ſoon convince of his ſin, for to that they will ſay, it is true, we are ſuch, it is an infirmity we cannot leave; but when he comes to deal with men about unbelief, telling them that they have no Faith, Oh what a do is there! oh
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:33158:29"/>how do their colours riſe! they are even ready to fly in his face, none will believe him, or be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced that he doth not believe; therefore labour to be convinced of unbelief.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Of Damnation, <hi>For he that believeth not ſhall be damned, Mark</hi> 16.16. which alſo is a thing that unbelievers will not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of; for tell them of it, and they will tell you, God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid, for God is merciful, and we hope to be ſaved as well as you; and not all the Miniſters in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> can make men believe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, till God give them a ſight of their unbelief; Then, O then, they can and will cry out, ſaying, Oh we ſhall be damned, and we cannot be ſaved; therefore la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to be convinced of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion alſo.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> You will ſay, if it be ſuch a hard thing to be ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:33158:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>then what ſhall we do to be convinced?</p>
                  <p>I <hi>Anſ.</hi> Pray to the Spirit, that you may be convinced by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, for it is his work, <hi>John</hi> 16.8.9. as thus, O bleſſed Spirit convince me of mine unbelief, for I muſt confeſs I am one that would not hitherto believe, that I do not believe. O open mine eies that I may ſee my unbelief, I humbly pray thee. Do the like for convictions about Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Take on, and begin to be troubled, as that poor man in the Goſpel, <hi>Mark</hi> 9.23, 24. who ſo cryed, and wept, and took on, and ſaid, <hi>Lord help mine unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief;</hi> and thoſe <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37. for elſe you build without a foundation, and then, how will your build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtand? There is a notable place for this in <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.23. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Faith came we were kept un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:33158:30"/>the Law, ſhut up unto the faith which ſhould afterwards be revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</hi> Mark, 1. Before Faith comes we are under the Law, that is, under the laſhes and terrors of the Law, eſpecially a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Faith cometh, indeed, we are whipt, and troubled indeed, by that grim Schoolmaſter whoſe name is Law. And 2. Before the Law comes we are ſhut up like Priſoners, and therefore muſt ſuffer as Priſoners. O my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, if then you mean to have Faith, you muſt not refuſe to be under the laſhes of the Law, you muſt be content to be in Priſon a while; and as Scholars which are grievouſly whipt, grievouſly to weep becauſe of your unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief; and becauſe of the miſeries which ſhall come upon you if ye believe not, <hi>For he that believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not ſhall be damned,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.16. Mark, he
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:33158:31"/>ſhall be damned, and what is that, you will ſay? Oh! it is to be ſentenced to Hell; and what is that? Oh! it is a place called
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Hieron.</hi> in <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.</note> 
                     <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henna,</hi> a word firſt of all uſed by Chriſt, &amp; afterwards by
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Sic<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in lib. Pir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keaboth admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt antiquo, cap.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.</note> others alſo for the place of the damned, and compounded of <hi>Gee</hi> and <hi>Hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom,</hi> which ſignifieth a Valley of <hi>Hinnom,</hi> which was a Valley nigh to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in which the old Idolatrous <hi>Jews</hi> were wont to burn their children alive to the honour of the Devil, at the ſounding of Trumpets and Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brels, and other loud ſounding inſtruments, that they might not hear the cry of their poor dying children, and for that the place was afterwards uſed for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of all filthineſs; as dung, carrion, and the like, and proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it is that our Saviour uſed this word above all other to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify the miſerable burning of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:33158:31"/>in that place, the pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful cries of the tormented, the barbarous and confuſed noiſe of the Tormentors, together with the moſt loathſome filthineſs of the place it ſelf. Go to now, ye Unbelievers, I ſay now as St.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>James</hi> once to rich men, and weep for the miſeries that ſhall come upon you in that woful place called <hi>Gehenna;</hi> nay go and howl together, O ye Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, and Uſurers, and Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and Adultereſſes, and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicators, and Harlots, and Swea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers; and Lyars, and covetous Worldlings, and riotous Livers; as ye were wont to be merry to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſome of you, ſo now, mourn and weep bitterly toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe you have no Faith, and becauſe you will and muſt, except you get Faith in Chriſt, lie and fry and burn like the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle children of the idolatrous
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:33158:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>Jews, in that woful place of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; thus howl together, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Oh that Valley of <hi>Hinnom!</hi> for ſo Hell is called; and, Oh that place of torment! where there is ſuch ſcreeching and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of men, women and children, that receptacle of all filth and filthy livers; Oh it will come for us, and for our portion! for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers (ſuch as we are) will be damned, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8.</p>
                  <p>I have read of one
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Rich. Baxter</hi> in his <hi>Everl. Reſt.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Brumo</hi> a famous Preacher in his time, that when he was dead and to be bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried he cryed out 3 times, 1. <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſatus ſum.</hi> 2. <hi>Judicatus ſum.</hi> 3. <hi>Damnatus ſum.</hi> I am 1. Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, 2. Judg'd, 3. Damn'd. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as both others, and himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that, verily thought he would ſurely be ſaved; ſo let every one of you, as dead and condemned by the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>John</hi> 3.18.</note> words of Chriſt, now ſay; Oh, I am Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:33158:32"/>I am Damned, I am Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. I thought once that I ſhould be ſaved aſſoon as any, and would not be otherwiſe perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but that my Soul ſhould be heavened as well as others; but now I ſee that unleſs infinite mercy do ſave me, and help me to believe in Chriſt, I ſhall be moſt certainly condemned by Chriſt. For <hi>he that believeth not is
<note n="†" place="margin">Enallage Temporis.</note> condemned already,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 3.18.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Deſire to believe, as he <hi>Mark</hi> 9.24. For a deſire of faith, if true, is faith; Or thus, as a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Downam</hi> in his Chriſtian warfare. c. 42.</note> Writer ſaith confidently. Our deſire of Grace, Faith, and Repentance, if true, are the Graces themſelves; at leaſt in God's acceptation, ſee <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.6. <hi>Bleſſed are they which hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and thriſt after righteouſneſs.</hi> Mark, they are bleſſed, who have ſuch gracious deſires, as are
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:33158:33"/>called hungring and thirſting; and therefore they cannot be without faith; and the cauſe hereof is the bleſſed
<note n="*" place="margin">Bleſſed <hi>Bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi>
                     </note> Nobleneſs of God's Nature, which by infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite diſtances doth tranſcend the nobleſt ſpirit upon earth, now men of ingenious diſpoſitions are wont to take ſweeteſt content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in prevailing over and gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the hearts, good wills, and affections of thoſe that wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them; how much more then muſt needs ſpiritual longings, gracious aſpires, and thirſty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires be kindly accepted with that moſt kind God; whoſe moſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving diſpoſition paſſeth all mens kindneſs; eſpecially ſith mens good turns, turn many times to our good and benefit, but <hi>our well doing extendeth not unto God, Pſal.</hi> 16.2. Were all the ſons of men <hi>Abrahams</hi> or Angels, and as many in number as the ſtars
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:33158:33"/>of Heaven, and as ſhining both with inward Graces, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward acts of piety, as they are in viſible glory; yet could they make no addition to that incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Majeſty above, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſo much as one drop to that boundleſs and bottomleſs Sea of goodneſs, or the leaſt glimpſe unto that Almighty Sun of glory. <hi>If thou be righteous, what giveſt thou unto him? or what receiveth he at thy hands? Thy wickedneſs may hurt a man as thou art, and thy righteouſneſs may profit the Son of man, Job.</hi> 35.6, 7, 8. Our holineſs helps him not; our ſins hurt him not; it is only for our good that God would do us good; no good nor gain accrues unto him by our goodneſs; for, what good can come by our imperfect goodneſs, to that which is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy infinitely good? What glory can be ſuperadded by our dim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:33158:34"/>to him which is already in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably glorious? Every in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite thing is naturally, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily uncapable of addition. Poſſibility of which ſuppoſed im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies contradiction, and deſtroys the nature of infiniteneſs, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (to return to my purpoſe) ſith deſires are excepted with God for deeds, let every one of you that would be aſſured of his ſalvation, deſire to believe to his ſalvation. It is reported of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> that when a certain poor ſtudent at <hi>Wittenberg</hi> would not be perſwaded by any to believe, or that he did believe, and ſo was exceedingly troubled in his mind, and left by all, he was ſent for, and when he came, did aſk him (when he ſaid he neither did nor could believe) but do not you deſire to believe? where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto the poor ſtudent replyed, yes, with all my heart I do deſire
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:33158:34"/>it, why then, ſaid <hi>Luther,</hi> you do believe; whereat the poor Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar was exceedingly comforted, ſatisfied, and perſwaded that he did believe: ſo you be ſatisfied in this point, that if you truly deſire to believe, you do believe. Our moſt gracious God
<note n="*" place="margin">As in <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Gen.</hi> 22.16, 17. read the place.</note> accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the will for the deed, and your affections for actions; and ſo long, ſo thirſt,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Dyke</hi> of ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceiving, cap. 19.</note> ſo hunger af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Faith, as a Fame-lik after meat, a <hi>Febricitant</hi> after drink, a Mendicant after a piece of ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and you ſhall be ſatisfied. <hi>For they that hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſs,</hi> and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently after Faith, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends Chriſts righteouſneſs, <hi>ſhall be ſatisfied. Mat.</hi> 5.6. and
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Bern. de Lect. Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel. Serm.</hi> 7.</note> ſo much as they can deſire, they ſhall receive.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Labor to ſee an excellency in Chriſt ſurpaſſing all things, and fixing thy heart upon him, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:33158:35"/>to ſeek him without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting; and ſeeking him, to ſell all for the gaining of him; like the Merchant in the Goſpel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, who ſeeking after him and met with him, and ſeeing him to be a
<note n="*" place="margin">For Chriſt is that pearl, <hi>Hilar. in Loc.</hi>
                     </note> pearl of great price; and ſo eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming him above all, ſold all and bought him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.45, 46.</p>
                  <p>For
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Rogers</hi> of <hi>Dedham</hi> in his Doctrine of Faith; e. 2. p. 128.</note> then is Faith begun, when namely, a man begins to be of <hi>Kilians,</hi> a Dutch School-maſters and bleſſed Martyrs mind; who being aſked if he loved not his Wife and Children? ſaid, Yes, if the World were gold, and were mine to diſpoſe of, I would give it to live with them, though it were but in priſon; yet my ſoul and Chriſt are dearer to me than all. O ſouls, ſouls, how do your hearts now ſtand affected? are ye ſo reſolved to ſell all? do you ſo prize Chriſt above all? will you ſeek after him upon ſuch
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:33158:35"/>terms? if you will, well; for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly you ſhall have him, and faith in him, and with him. O my God, help this people ſo to prize thy Son; help thy Sons to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in thy Son. I humbly pray thee.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Labour to have your hearts over-powered with the evidence of truth and reaſon: For we find by experience, that though truth and reaſon, and conſcience, and all make for it, ſo as that we may truly ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to what is ſaid; yet the heart is ſtubborn, and will not yield, but ſtands out like a contentious Adverſarie, which, though he be overthrown in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry trial, yet will begin again. So the heart, though it be anſwered and overcome with Arguments, and Pleas, and Reaſons again and again; yet will begin again to plead againſt it ſelf: For, ſay ſome, when they are non-ſuited,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:33158:36"/>and have nothing to ſay; Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are mercifull, and good Chriſtians compaſſionate, &amp; will not diſcourage us; but did they know our hearts, what baſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean Cages they be, they would judge otherwiſe than they do. Therefore I ſay, give over quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling, and be ſatisfied and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, when Truth and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon tell ye, that ye ought to yeild, and to believe; becauſe the Lord of Life and God of Truth hath ſaid, <hi>Him that cometh to me,</hi> whatſoever his heart be, or have been, and whatſoever his former life have been; for he ſaith not, unleſſe he have a baſe, filthy heart. Again, him that cometh to me, though he have been the vileſt wretch that ever the Earth bore, though a notorious <hi>Belialiſt,</hi> a beaſtly liver, a filthy fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, an inſatiable Drunkard, an unreaſonable Extortioner, <hi>I will
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:33158:36"/>in no wiſe caſt him out, John</hi> 6.37. O my Brethren! what could Chriſt ſay more? Chriſt you ſee ſpeaks for you; and will you have us ſpeak againſt you? nay, will you ſpeak againſt your ſelves! O be overcome by Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, overcome by Truth; for Reaſon tels you, that you ought to yield, when your Reaſons are anſwered; and Truth commands you to ſubmit, when you are ſo well promiſed by the God of Truth.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Beg Faith, for it is the gift of God, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.29. ſay, as <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel, Give me children or elſe I die, Gen.</hi> 30.1. So, Lord, give me Faith, or elſe I die, and he will not ſay thee nay. For <hi>eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that asketh, receiveth,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.9. Aſk therefore and ſay, Lord, thou haſt ſaid, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that aſketh receiveth; O let me receive for one, or how
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:33158:37"/>elſe can it be every one, if I may not for one; Prayer is the ſouls recourſe to the fountain of life, and a Chriſtians addreſs to the God of all power, to fetch pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and help in a time of need, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. <hi>ult.</hi> Go therefore, O dear Chriſtians, to the Chriſtians God, for power and help in this time of need; Go, and cry, and ſay with that poor man in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, <hi>Lord help mine unbelief, Mar.</hi> 9.24. Lord help my poor ſoul to believe; Beloved, no leſs power is here required for you to be able to believe, being dead; than was for the raiſing of Chriſt from the dead, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.19.20. ſee the place; and place your ſelves therefore before his Throne of grace, that you may get grace and power to believe, according to the working of his mighty power, which he wrought in Chriſt when he raiſed him
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:33158:37"/>from the dead, and ſet him at his own right hand in heavenly places. And thus beg power to believe, and to be good, and do not think that it is in
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Platonici &amp; Stoici aiunt apud</hi> Clem. Alex. l. 1. c. 61</note> your po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to have faith in God, when all your power muſt come from God;
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Videatur Concil. Arau ſ. c.</hi> 24.</note> It is man's greateſt weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to preſume upon his own ſtrength, when his greateſt ſtrength is but weakneſs; and therefore I preſs and perſwade you to beg, which if ye do as ye ought, I aſſure you in the words of Chriſt, that it will not be long before you get faith in Chriſt, &amp; not long neither before ye will be bleſſed with that heavenly Aſſurance of the Saints which cometh by Chriſt, Chriſt not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to deny you, becauſe <hi>he cannot deny himſelf,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.13. and not deny himſelf, becauſe he is Truth it ſelf, <hi>John</hi> 14.6. and being Truth it ſelf, hath ſaid; <hi>Ask
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:33158:38"/>and you ſhall have; ſeek, and you ſhall find; knock, and it ſhall be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened unto you, Luke</hi> 11.9.</p>
                  <p>Thus labour by all theſe holy waies and means to believe, and when your carnal friends ſhall go about to hinder thee, ſaying; what needs all this praying, and all this weeping, and all this run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to Sermons? ſay, would ye not have me to live? if I do not believe I cannot live: Again, ſay, Would ye have me be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of nothing? I will be (by Gods grace) aſſured of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and eſpecially of my ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. Again, if Satan ſeek to hinder you from ſtriving and praying that ye may not believe, yet pray, and uſe all the means premiſed; becauſe God hath promiſed that you ſhall be heard; and he will do his beſt for you, when Satan ſhall do his worſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you.</p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:33158:38"/>
                  <p>The Lord give you hearts to pray, and hearts to believe, that believing you may be aſſured that you ſhall be ſaved; ſo pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from his heart your faithful friend, to his &amp; your beſt friend, who is a hearer of prayers, and can do abundantly above all that you or I can ask or think, or conceive; <hi>to him be glory in the Church by Chriſt Jeſus, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all ages, world without end,
<note n="3" place="margin">Medium. Now this and the reſt of the enſuing Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diums are properly and chiefly provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for Saints, who do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, for which cauſe and for whoſe ſake I call this Tract the Saints Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance <hi>à potio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri.</hi>
                        </note> Amen, Eph.</hi> 3.20.21.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Labour to live as ſpotleſs a life as you can poſſibly; <hi>for
<note n="*" place="margin">1 Joh. 3.3.</note> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man that hath this hope in him;</hi> What hope? that he ſhall ſee God, <hi>v.</hi> 2. namely, in
<note n="‖" place="margin">
                        <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> l. 4. <hi>c</hi> 37.</note> Chriſt, and by himſelf, <hi>purifieth himſelf even as he is pure.</hi> Obſerve, <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man that hath this hope;</hi> and ſo conſequently, whoſe ſoul is ſafe; whoſe faith is ſound; whoſe heart is ſure: Again, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, <hi>purifies himſelf;</hi> that is,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:33158:39"/>labours to be pure; and how is that? <hi>even as he,</hi> namely, God himſelf, <hi>is pure.</hi> O height of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs! O profunditie of purity! are there any ſuch in the world? ſay the men of the world; Yes, ſaith the Apoſtle, there are ſuch, which though they are not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin, yet are not
<note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.9. &amp; 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.9.</note> under ſin; that is, under a reigning ſin, preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing hard towards perfection; which is to be pure as he is pure; that is, aſpiring to it, and climb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after it, and towards it, as <hi>Johnathan</hi>'s Armor-bearer after his Maſter. I remember what a
<note n="*" place="margin">Anſelm, de Simil.</note> Father ſaith, that he had rather be in Hell, than lie in any ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God: and I have been much taken with his ſaying; God grant that by it you alſo may be ſo taken, as that you may not be ſo often overtaken; But to the Law and Teſtimony for all the Fathers: <hi>Who is ſhe that looketh
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:33158:39"/>forth as the morning; fair as the Moon, clear as the Sun? Cant.</hi> 6.10. Obſerve, how Chriſt praiſeth his Church, for her tranſcendent pureneſs, and ſurpaſſing fairneſs. Some ſpots ſhe hath, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe is aſſimilated to the Moon as well as Sun; and yet called fair, becauſe ſhe alloweth them not; and becauſe of that Chriſt ſeeth them not: No, no, even <hi>Balaam</hi> could ſay, <hi>He hath not beheld iniquity in Jacob, neither hath he ſeen perverſneſs in Iſrael, Numb.</hi> 23.21. Again, <hi>She is fair as the morning;</hi> for ſhe is
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Inſtar dilu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi quando aurera incipit tenebras diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellere.</hi> Parae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</note> partly clear, and partly dim, like that wonderfull day which is only known to the Lord, not day nor night, <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.7. for ſo is the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Vide</hi> Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſt. <hi>in Rom.</hi> 13.12.</note> Morning, and ſo is ſhe; not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together day, becauſe of ſin re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining in her, nor altogether night, becauſe of ſin reſiſted by her; and ſo, and after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:33158:40"/>fair and clear and pure: but farther, what ſaith Chriſt of her? <hi>Thou art all fair, my love, there is no ſpot in thee, Cant.</hi> 4.7. that is, no ſpot
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.15.</note> allowed, no ſpot ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved; for whilſt ſhe is able to ſtand ſhe ſtands, and
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.4.</note> ſtriveth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſin: ſo do you, labouring <hi>to cleanſe your ſelves from all fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs of fleſh and ſpirit,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. and that <hi>by the Spirit, Rom.</hi> 8.13. For as any one blemiſh in the face mars beauty, and one dram of poiſon ſpoils a whole box of precious Ointment: ſo if you let alone but one ſin to reign in you, and over you, that one will ſpoil all, even all your fair car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and all your confidence; for no
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Si unum in locum collata ſint, omnia mala cum tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitudinis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo non erunt comparanda.</hi> Cicoro 2. <hi>Thuſc.</hi>
                     </note> evil like the evil of ſin to ſpoil a man. When <hi>Phocas,</hi> the Roman Emperor had built a moſt fair and ſtately Pallace, there was a voice heard in the night, <hi>Sin within will deſtroy all:</hi> So,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:33158:40"/>when we have built Caſtles in the air, and by our fair and ſpecious performances have gotten ſome Aſſurance &amp; confidence towards God, but afterward give way to one ſin or other, we ſhall hear one time or other a voice from within, <hi>Sin within will deſtroy all,</hi> our own conſciences
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.15.</note> accuſing us, yea, condemning us for the ſame, and
<note n="‖" place="margin">So the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Jonah</hi> loſt his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence by his diſobedience. Dr. <hi>King</hi> on <hi>Jonah</hi> 1.6.</note> taking away our Aſſurance from us, for ſin allowed by us. Let us fall therefore upon ſin, and deſtroy it, that ſins puniſhment may not fall upon us, and deſtroy us, and our confidence with us. Oh that this people were wiſe! Oh that they would ſo ſtrive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſin, and againſt every ſin! Oh that they would unreſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cleanſe their hands! Oh that they would thorowly purifie their hearts, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.8. and cleanſe them from luſt, even every luſt! Oh that I could help them! Oh
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:33158:41"/>that I could even pull them away from their beloved ſins! for then they ſhould not live, or lodge in and with any of them one day, or one night longer: well, you muſt do this work with God's help; therefore go every one of you and kill every one of them; ſpare none, no, not the leaſt; Oh ſave none alive, to be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that God will ſave you alive; elſe you cannot be ſo perſwaded as long as any one ſin is by you allowed: thus labour to purifie your ſelves, and to deſtroy ſin, and when you have ſo done, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to keep your ſelves ſo; and if the Tempter re-aſſault you, do you alſo re-encounter him, and that with the Word, for that is a Chriſtians ſword: tell him as the Spouſe told Chriſt in another ſence, <hi>I have waſhed my feet, how ſhall I defile then<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>? Cant.</hi> 5.3. Oh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> I cannot; Oh! I will not, by
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:33158:41"/>God's help. When Satan came to Chriſt he found nothing in him, but when he comes to you, he finds much in you, even much corruption; but do you <hi>reſiſt him in the faith:</hi> I ſay
<note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.9.</note> as <hi>Peter,</hi> that that which he findes in you, may not be found to be yours, but his; becauſe you do not own it, but reſiſt it, to be aſſured, as then you
<note n="*" place="margin">Damaſc. Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror de Perſer.</note> may be, that you ſhall be ſaved. Nay, crie to God to keep you; for it is not as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcene</hi> and others teach, in the power of man to hold out; no, no, <hi>we are kept by the power of God, through faith to ſalvation.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. and therefore you muſt beg this power of God,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> and that very much and often, yea, continually; for then Satan will not be able to harm you. It is ſtoried of a malicious woman, that ſhe gave her ſelf to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, provided he would do a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:33158:42"/>to ſuch a Neighbour, whom ſhe deadly hated; the Devil went once and again to do his work; but at laſt returns, and tels her, that he could not hurt him, becauſe he found him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies praying, or reading: do you likewiſe; pray ſo alwaies, and you will alſo ſpeed as he did; eſpecially then when Satan tempts you to make you fall; then do you fall to your prayers and ſay; Lord, this is the power and hour of darkneſſe; now therefore keep me in this hour of temptation, that I may keep up the Aſſurance of my Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Make your calling and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſure;</hi>
                     <note n="4" place="margin">Medium.</note> for then you alſo make Heaven ſure, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1, 5, 6. <hi>giving all diligence, add to your faith vertue, &amp;c.</hi> And then, <hi>v.</hi> 11. <hi>ſo an entrance ſhall be adminiſtred unto you abundantly, into the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:33158:42"/>Kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> I pay you obſerve your work; you muſt become good Arithmeticians, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the perfect Rule of <hi>Addition,</hi> to be certain of your everlaſting ſalvation: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore go, and add vertue to ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and ſtill ſay; But do I not miſ-reckon? Am I in the right? Do I not miſs temperance though I have knowledge. And do I not want patience, though I have temperance? Is not godlineſswan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting-though patience be not? Is not brotherly kindneſs forgotten by me though godlineſs be not? Have I not left out Charitie, though I do not miſs Brotherly kindneſs? Are all the Graces of Gods Spirit here? and if any be wanting, go, and reckon again, and make a farther Addition; more eſpecially if Patience be wanting in thy reckoning; Go,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:33158:43"/>and write, I ſhould ſay, add pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, the like may be ſaid of all the reſt; and ſo labour to be compleat in Grace, having in you every Grace, and ſtriving ſtill to have more Grace, even more of every Grace; for though, if we believe in Chriſt we are ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in every part, yet are we ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified but in part; even as <hi>we
<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 13.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> know but in part,</hi> ſo that we ſhall need ſtill to add ſomewhat to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very part, if in the Saints Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance we would have our part; Nay, had need to give all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, as the Apoſtle tels us, <hi>v.</hi> 5. by our continual additions to make our calling, and election, and ſalvation ſure, and to live an extraordinarie holy, ſtrict, and Seraphical life to attain to it. I knew a moſt eminent holy walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er once, his name was <hi>Ignatius Jourdan</hi> a Juſtice of the Peace, who was after his converſion al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:33158:43"/>aſſur'd of his ſalvation, as he told me; but the courſe that he took was this, he would every morning riſe at 3 of the Clock, as I was told, and ſpend his time in prayer, reading, and medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, till 7, and then do juſtice to all that came to him: Again, he would puniſh any for ſwearing, and other offences, if he were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo great; and I never heard a vain, or evil word come out of his mouth, but he would be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies talking of Heaven: do you live ſuch an holy, and heavenly life too, and give all diligence thereunto, and you will be ſure alſo, as he was, of Heaven.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Ger the pardon of your ſins ſealed,
<note n="5" place="margin">Medium.</note> for what is remiſſion of ſin but juſtification from ſin? Now, <hi>whom he juſtifieth, he alſo glorifleth, Rom.</hi> 8.30. Again, what is it but a covering of ſin? and what ſaith <hi>David</hi> of that? <hi>Bleſſed
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:33158:44"/>is he whoſe ſin is covered,</hi> in <hi>Pſ.</hi> 32.1. ſo that if I can but know that my ſins are forgiven me, I may know alſo that Heaven will be given me; Wherefore be ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, even importunately earneſt with God to have thy ſins forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thee by God, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.19. you may ſee how earneſt and eager he was in this thing, ſaying, <hi>O Lord, O Lord forgive, O Lord hearken and do;</hi> Never was a condemned Malefactor ſo earneſt for a pardon with his King. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was a poor Mendicant ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate for a piece of bread, or for an Alms with his rich Neighbor, as he for a pardon with his God and King, and ſo muſt you be, and therefore even preſs into the preſence of God, for thy pardon to be ſealed by God; Go and cry, ſaying, O God forgive, O God forget, O God
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.</note> blot out all my tranſgreſſions,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:33158:44"/>and cleanſe me throughly from my ſins; O
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.19.</note> Lord hear, O Lord defer not for thy own ſake; here be more than ordinarily fervent, and inſtant; for the pardon of ſin is the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Carde &amp; caput foederis.</hi> Paraeus.</note> principal thing in the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace ſo much urged, and to be preſſed in prayer; he that is ſure of that, may be ſure alſo of God's being reconciled to him in Chriſt; Chriſt making for him his peace, peace paſſing all his underſtanding, his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding now knowing that he ſhall have life everlaſting. I for my part am therefore wont to be more large and more earneſt in this, than in any other part of my more ſolemn ſupplications, and I deſire, and ſtrive ſtill to be ſo prolix, and ſo long in this thing, till I have my errands end, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe I am loath to make an end, and I have found much ſucceſs and comfort in it, to God's glory
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:33158:45"/>be it ſpoken, I pray you, do ye pray ſo too; and withall take this Corollary with you.</p>
                  <p>When you are upon your knees aſking God forgiveneſs,
<note place="margin">A Corollary.</note> have in readineſs a Catalogue of your many and knowable ſins, either in your memories, or in writing, and ſpread them all before the Lord, as once
<note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 37.14.</note> 
                     <hi>Hezekiah Rabſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ka's</hi> letter, for then you are moſt like to ſpeed, becauſe it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly written, <hi>That if we confeſs our ſins God is faithful and juſt to forgive us our ſins, and to cheanſe us from all unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> I <hi>John</hi> 1.9. and you will be able then thus to plead with God, when you aſk pardon of God; O God thou haſt ſaid, if they ſhall confeſs their iniquities, then will I remember my Covenant, <hi>Lev.</hi> 26.40, 42. and lo, we O Lord confeſs here our iniquities before thee, O do thou therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:33158:45"/>the Covenant made by thee, whoſe capital matter is the forgiveneſs of our ſins. Again, you may then plead that famous place in <hi>Job</hi> 37.27. <hi>He looketh upon men, and if any ſay,</hi> Mark, if any ſay, and ſo if any of us here ſhall ſay ſo, <hi>I have ſinned perverted that which was right, and it profited me not, He will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver his Soul;</hi> as thus, we may ſay, Lord it is written, and ſaid of thee (likewiſe ſhew him the book, the chapter, the place wherein this precious Scripture lies) That thou lookeſt upon men, and if any ſay, I have ſinned, thou wilt deliver his Soul. O look upon us therefore here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate before thee, or in the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular upon me, a poor ſinner here lying before thee, and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſaying, thus and thus I have ſinned, and deliver my poor Soul, Oh! my poor Soul from hell,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:33158:46"/>and death, and damnation, I pray thee having forgiven me all my ſins, for it is ſaid, If any ſhall ſay I have ſinned, now Lord, I ſay, and ſay it from my heart; therefore O God forgive me, O Lord waſh me, and pardon all my offences, for they are won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous great, but not too great for ſo great a God to forgive. Thus confeſs, and ſo crave the pardon of thy ſins, and withall to have the pardon of them
<note n="*" place="margin">Eph. 1.13. 2 Cor. 1.22.</note> ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, that is to be aſſured by the Spirit that they are pardoned, as <hi>David</hi> was, when he ſaid, <hi>Thou forgaveſt the iniquity of my ſin, Selah, Pſal.</hi> 22. O Sirs, here is work for you, to have ſin not only pardoned, but alſo to be perſwaded that it is par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, which is a thing not ſo eaſily obtained, as is commonly believed, No, no you muſt ſweat about it, and labour hard to have
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:33158:46"/>it done, if you deſire to be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that you ſhall be ſaved.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Get an undeceiving taſt of the joys of Heaven, as thoſe Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers did, which were ſo ſure of their ſalvation, <hi>v.</hi> 8. For then you alſo muſt needs be ſure of your reception, entrance and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion into Heaven; becauſe they are fore-runners, and the earneſt of it, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.14. the Greek is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, which properly is part of a price promiſed to be paid (
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Vulteius in ſua Juriſpr. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 30. Diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it from Hypotheca, as being move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, whereas Hypotheca is not.</note> 
                     <hi>Civilians</hi> call it a pledge) as here, part of the joys of Heaven promiſed to us, to be enjoyed by us hereafter; And theſe joys are ſo great for their quantity, and ſo ſweet for their quality, as that I hope I ſhall not need to preſs you overmuch to the gaining of them; For are they not moſt ſweetly reſembled to Apples, to
<note n="*" place="margin">Cant. 2.5.</note> Flagons, to ‖ Mannah, all which things though they are ſo
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ibid. id eſt ſalutari potio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Jeſu Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte.</hi> Jun &amp; Tremel.</note>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 2.17.</note>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:33158:47"/>exceeding ſweet, yet cannot poſſibly come near or match thoſe joys which without all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of compariſon, and meaſure of proportion do ſurmount and ſurpaſs the ſame; even infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, infinitely, <hi>For they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable and full of glory,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſpeakable;</hi> were all the world full of Orators, and all they like Angels, ſpeaking with the tongues of Angels, and able to utter their minds, and to pour out their conceptions with tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents of elocution, yet would not they be able to expreſs thoſe joys.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Full of glory. The great, and main Ocean is not ſo full of water, though it be
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Mare nil niſi aquae.</hi> Owen.</note> nothing but water, nor the ſpangled ſkie ſo full of Stars, nor the gay dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery of the earth ſo full of flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, as they are full of glory. Methought I was in a Tryumph,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:33158:47"/>and even covered and deck'd all over and over, and over with moſt refulgent beams of glory, when it pleaſed God all-graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, to make my unworthy ſelf a partaker of thoſe joyes which are ſo full of glory. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, oh! how ſhould your Souls be now enamoured with them, and long, and labour after them? O Souls, Souls here are Apples, flagons, here ſhowers of Mannah for you to be had by you. Oh! go after them, Oh! get them, for the Aſſurance of Salvation lieth in, and thorow them to be had by them.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                     </label> 2. You will ſay,
 how ſhall we get them?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>I Anſ.</hi> Beg them,
 for Chriſt hath promiſed them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Where?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>I Anſ. Rev.</hi> 2.17.
 Read the place; And ſo place your ſelves again before the Lord Chriſt;
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:33158:48"/>and ſay; Lord, give us, or me, in the ſingular, this Mannah, this ſweet bread of of Heaven; Oh ſhowre it down upon my poor Soul, and having taſted it, may be thereby aſſured; that as I have been fed with Angels food on earth; ſo I ſhall feed on the Angels bread in Heaven. But here</p>
                  <p>A Caſe of conſcience comes to be reſolved,
<note place="margin">A Caſe of Conſcience.</note> for you will ſay happily, Sir, we have begged theſe joyes; and yet cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy them; and therefore tell us what we muſt do in ſuch a caſe?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwered. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>I Anſwer,</hi>
 It may be you have left undone ſome thing, which ye ought to have done; and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the fore mentioned promiſe was made, I mean overcoming; for ſo ſaith Chriſt, <hi>To him that overcometh will I give to eat of the hidden Mannah, Rev.</hi> 2.17. Now if ſo, then you muſt for the obtaining of them covercome.</p>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:33158:48"/>
                  <p n="1">1. Satan <hi>by the blood of the Lamb, Rev.</hi> 12.11.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The World by faith, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.4.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Your ſelves
<note n="‖" place="margin">Matt. 16.24.</note> denying your ſelves in many things, which as yet you have not denied your ſelves in, as in meats, in ſleep, in pleaſures, in the putting on of Apparel, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. God himſelf, as <hi>Jocob</hi> did the <hi>Patriarch,</hi> eſpecially when you beg thoſe joyes. Beloved, never did
<note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 16.21.</note> 
                     <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſo beg crumbs that fell from <hi>Dives</hi> his table; nor
<note n="‖" place="margin">Judg. 4.19.</note> 
                     <hi>Siſera</hi> beg drink of <hi>Jael</hi> which then gave him milk to drink, as that holy man did beg thoſe crumbs of comfort, which he wanted; and that glorious viſion of <hi>Jehovah</hi>'s face, which he to ſee ſo deſired, when he ſaid, <hi>I'le not leave thee; till thou bleſs me;</hi> conſtraining God thereby to bleſs his wreſtling, with the
<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 32.</note>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:33158:49"/>ſight of refulgent beams of the light of his pleaſed, and pleaſant countenance, which runs parel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel with the joys of Heaven, and are infinitly ſweeter then <hi>Jael</hi>'s milk, which ſhe gave <hi>Siſera</hi> to drink in a Lordly diſh; yea, than all the milk of all the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> flowing with milk and honey; O let your earneſtneſs, and importunity match his; and let every one of you, now ſay after him; Lord I will not leave thee till thou bleſs me, as thou did'ſt bleſs him with a glimpſe, and glance of the light of thy countenance; or thus, as the Spouſe of Chriſt, ſaid to Chriſt in the
<note n="*" place="margin">Cant. 2.5.</note> Canticles; ſo ſay thou to him, in thine heart, and in thy Cloſet, comfort me, oh me alſo! with apples, even the ſweet apples of they divine Conſolations, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed from thy moſt
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Expoſ.</hi> 3. <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum in Loc.</hi>
                     </note> ſweet, and holy word; and ſtay me with
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:33158:49"/>flagons, even flagons of love, for I am
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>ſagitia amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris iſtius con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixa.</hi> Theodor. <hi>in Loc.</hi>
                     </note> ſick of love. O my love do not, O do not deny me thy love; O my joy, do not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold from me thy joy. Or thus, O my dear, thou haſt ſaid to him that overcometh, will I give to eat of the hidden Mannah; and wilt thou not give to me that Mannah, who come to thee for it's Manducation, to be aſſured of my Salvation; O my God, thou haſt promiſed it to him that overcometh; and loe, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to overcome, and to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Satan by thy blood; my ſelf, by thy love; the world by my Faith; and thy ſelf by my prayers, and for that end am now come to overcome both my ſelf, and thee; Oh! give me therefore, &amp; let me have, what here I crave, even that Mannah which thou haſt promiſed me, and that joy unſpeakable, and full of glory.</p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:33158:50"/>
                  <p n="7">7. Nay,
<note n="7" place="margin">Medidum.</note> beg this great Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance it ſelf, and beg it much, for it is a gift worth your aſking, and all pains taking with it, they that have it are
<note n="*" place="margin">In Angeli ſtatum prove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hit. Euſeb. Euriſ. hom. de Epiph.</note> Angelized by the Spirit, extatized in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and emparadized in God; God being their Aſſurer, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by this aſſurance, becomes their exceeding great reward; As for their life, it is the life of Heaven, as their joy is the joy of Heaven, Heaven being in their hearts, their hearts in Heaven. Labour therefore, dear hearts, for this Aſſurance, begging it of God, who is both able and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to give it to thoſe that aſk it; Aſk it therefore, and when you aſk it do as <hi>Achſah Caleb's</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which wanting ſprings of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, came to her Father, lighted off from her Aſs, and ſaid, <hi>Give me a bleſſing, for thou haſt given me a South-land, give me alſo
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:33158:50"/>ſprings of water, Judg.</hi> 1.14. anſwerably whereunto, do you alſo light off from your moſt eager purſuit after the gains, profits, emoluments, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments of this preſent world, and falling down before your heavenly father, ſay; Father, give me a bleſſing, for thou haſt given me theſe outward things, and I want nothing but only the aſſurance of my Salvation; give me therefore ſprings of water al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo; that is, the aſſurance of mine eternal bliſs, which is like ſprings of water, yea, Fountains of liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing water ſpringing from that O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean and Sea of ineffable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, which are in thy bleſſed ſelf. O bleſſed Father, give me both the upper ſprings, and the neither ſprings as
<note n="*" place="margin">Judg. 1.14.</note> 
                     <hi>Caleb</hi> did his Daughter.</p>
                  <p>The upper ſprings hereafter in Heaven; to wit, the joyes of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:33158:51"/>in Heaven, and the neither ſprings; I mean, the aſſurance of Heaven here upon earth; I humbly pray thee, thus beg, and beg as earneſtly, and ardently as a beggar begs his alms, becauſe he needs it; ſo you this aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, becauſe you cannot well live without it; I told you of a very holy man,
<note n="*" place="margin">Juſtice Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan.</note> a Juſtice of the Peace; how holily he lived to gain his aſſurance; and now, let me tell you, what once he ſaid to a Viſitant that came to ſee him. How is it with you? Are you aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red now of your Salvation, or are you not yet? And, when the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitant anſwered no. He told him, were it my caſe, I would go to my Cloſet, and ſhut my door and never leave begging it of God, till I had it beſtowed on me, by God. Beloved, this was good Counſel; whether the Viſitant fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed it or no, I know not, but
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:33158:51"/>do you follow it, and ſo go, O go, and betake your ſelves to your Cloſets, again upon this account alſo; &amp; ſhut your doors, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.6. and pray to your heavenly Father which is in ſecret that he will give you this aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of your Salvation, which will reward you amplie and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly, for all your paines taking in ſuch a ſupplication; O Souls, when once ye are in, never come out,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 8</note> till aſſurance comes in. Nay, go, and tell God ſo, thou that heareſt me this day, and wanteſt this aſſurance, Lord, I will not go hence, till thou give it me, for thou haſt ſaid; <hi>Ask, &amp; it ſhall be given to you, Luk <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 9. and do not doubt, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade thy ſelf for certain, that as <hi>Caleb, Achſah</hi> her Father gave his Daughter, petitioning him, both the * upper-ſprings,
<note place="margin">Judg. 1.14.</note> and the neither ſprings which ſhe
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:33158:52"/>wanted;
<note place="margin">See <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.11, 12, 13.</note> ſo your heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in reſpect of whoſe tender compaſſions and bowels of pity, the kindeſt Father's greateſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is but harſhneſs; in reſpect of whoſe incomparably melting and ſweeteſt inclination; the moſt loving Nature of any man living is but moroſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ty, will give you alſo this by you ſo begged and petitioned Aſſurance of your ſouls ſalvation.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. <note n="8" place="margin">Medium.</note> Get the Spirits teſtimony of which we read <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16. <hi>The Spirit himſelf bears witneſs to our Spirits, that we are the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, and if children then heirs;</hi> that follows <hi>v.</hi> 17. and therefore this Aſſurance of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation muſt needs follow. Mark, here are two witneſſes to aſſure us of our both filiation and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Our own ſpirit, How? our own Spirit? what more deceitful
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:33158:52"/>than a mans own
<note n="*" place="margin">Jer. 17.9.</note> heart? but ſtay, it is not the carnal heart; but theregenerate heart, as the word ſpirit is taken, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11. whence
<note n="*" place="margin">Origines in Loc.</note> 
                     <hi>Origen.</hi> The Spirit bears witneſs, not to the Soul, but to the Spirit, that is, the heart regenerated by the Spirit, which goes for ſence, and feeling, and finding it ſelf to have Faith in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and truly to be regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Spirit, is able to ſay truly with the Apoſtle, <hi>I know whom I have believed,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12. and <hi>I am crucified with Chriſt, nevertheleſs I live, yet not I, but Chriſt lives in me, Gal.</hi> 2.20. ſee the place. <hi>Stapleton</hi> that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Popiſh Writer, would have this witneſs to be our charity, but there is not a ſyllable for it in the Text; and therefore his aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I reject for falſe.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond witneſs is the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God; who as a <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:33158:53"/>Co-witneſs ſteps in, and confirms what our own ſpirit affirms, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; it is true, thou art a child of God; But how ſhall I know that this teſtimony is not a delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but the Spirits truly? Thus you may be ſure of it, ſaith a worthy Writer. Either it is the Spirits or the fleſhes perſwaſion; Not the fleſhes, for that doth not lead us, nor adduce us to divine, and heavenly things, therefore the Spirits, and the Spirit doth not lie.
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Bellarm. l.</hi> 3. <hi>de juſtif. c.</hi> 9.</note> Thus he. <hi>Bell armine</hi> ſaith that this teſtimony of the Spirit begets but a conjectural certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of our ſalvation; but that is as falſe as God is true, for can any thing be more true and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, than that which is aſſerted by the God of truth? well then, here are two Witneſſes for you, and you know what the Law ſaith, that <hi>at the mouth of two Witneſſes, matters ſhall be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:33158:53"/>Deut.</hi> 19.15. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore why ſhould ye doubt? <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi> upon this place triumphs as it were, ſaying;
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> in <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16. to be noted againſt <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines</hi> conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctural Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</note> What ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guity is there then left for us? if a Man, Angel, or Arch-Angel promiſe a thing, a man may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily doubt, but ſith the ſupreme eſſence of God's Spirit, who makes us pray, promiſes to them that pray, and performs what he promiſes, doth ſo bear witneſs within us, what room is left for heſitating and doubting to us? Labour therefore for this teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the Spirit.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> But you will ſay,
<note place="margin">Qneſt.</note> How ſhall we come by it?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>I Anſw.</hi>

                     <note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 11.15.</note> Crave it, as thus, O bleſſed Spirit, bear witneſs to my Spirit, that I am a child of God: <hi>Veniſancte Spiritus,</hi> Come O holy Spirit, and tell my Spirit ſo, that my Spirit may rejoyce
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:33158:54"/>in the God of my ſalvation, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſured of my ſalvation. Men ſuppine men to be witneſſes for them; but do you only intreat the Spirit to be a witneſs for you, and he will be willing to do it for you; For as Chriſt ſaith of the Father, <hi>The Father himſelf loveth you, John</hi> 16.27. ſo I of the Spirit; The Spirit himſelf, who is one with the Father, loveth you. Therefore go again, and again to the Spirit, and pray to the ſame effect, ſaying, Holy Spirit, ſpeak to my Spirit, and ſpeak plain, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſo plain as that I may know that it is thy voice, and not the voice of a ſtranger, for thy ſheep do not love to hear the voice of
<note n="*" place="margin">Joſſ. 10.4, 5. Joh. 10.3.</note> ſtrangers; Nay, come bleſſed Spirit and call me, as it were by my
<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 22.17.</note> name, as Chriſt calls his ſheep by name, ſaying, <hi>Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, John, Peter, Mary,</hi> thou art a Child of God. O ſirs, let every
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:33158:54"/>one that heareth me this day ſay ſo; come bleſſed Spirit, come, and teſtifie ſo, and he that ſhall come will come, and will not tarry, and when he cometh, Aſſurance cometh, for he comes not alone, when he cometh, but his reward is with him, and before him, to wit, his teſtimony, and his ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.22. which is the exceeding great reward of our ſupplications, and the merciful compenſation of a truly graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous converſation.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. <note n="9" place="margin">Medium.</note> But I have one help more for you, and that is, you muſt try your ſelves daily by ſome evid en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for Heaven; When a Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, being bent for a certain place, and told by ſigns and tokens which is the way to it; as namely, there are ſuch Meadows at the one hand, which he muſt paſs by; ſuch miry places at the other, which he muſt leave, and ſuch
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:33158:55"/>Mountains before him, which he muſt paſs over, and he findes it ſo, he is ſure that he is in his right way, and ſhall certainly come to the place appointed; For, ſaith he, when he is paſt the places ſpoken of; lo, there be the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, the miry places, the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains which I was told of, I am paſt them; now a child of God being bound and bent for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is ſuch a Traveller too, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.6. and * thus rendred in your Engliſh meetre.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 24.6.</note> 
                     <hi>This is the brood of Travellers, in ſeeking of his grace: As</hi> Jacob <hi>did the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralite, in that time of his race.</hi> And this Traveller is told in the holy Scriptures, and by us Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters which is the way to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and how he ſhall know that he is in his way, and ſhall certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly arrive there; As for example, ſuch ſins and waies, which are
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:33158:55"/>like miry places, and meadows muſt be left on the right, and on the left hand, and that ſuch and ſuch duties and perfections, which are like high and craggy Mountains he muſt go over, whereupon it followeth, that when he looketh back into his life and courſes, and finds it to be ſo as he was told, he muſt needs be aſſured that for certain he ſhall be ſaved; for ſaith he, are not theſe ſins which I have left, the miry places which I was told of? and theſe pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon which I have paſſed by, the pleaſant meadows which I was told of? and thoſe difficult duties which I have laboured to perform, as believing, ſelf deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, a ſpotleſs walking, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, and laborious ſerving of God, even day and night, the high and craggy mountains which I was fore-ſhown? Beloved, it is
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:33158:56"/>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Nichols</hi> hath it, in his life.</note> reported of that holy man <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius Jordan;</hi> whom I former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mentioned, that when he was near his end, and one did aſk him, how he did, and could ſo keep up and maintain his Aſſurance ſo conſtantly, even to the end? he anſwered, that every day, he did try himſelf, by ſome undeceiving ſignes; and evidences for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, &amp; that kept it up, &amp; ſo died. Do you therefore likewiſe as he did, and you may be aſſured as he was.</p>
                  <p>But I know, you will be very inquiſitive now, what thoſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences are, whereby you are to try your ſelves ſo; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beſides that which hath bin already ſpoken, I ſhall give you a more full information about it, and ſhew you more directly, which they are, out of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15. Where they lie even evidently before you. For there the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:33158:56"/>ſtates the Queſtion, who ſhall be ſaved; ſaying, <hi>Lord, who ſhall dwell in thy Tabernacle? Who ſhall dwell in thy holy Hill?</hi> mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Heaven, which is called <hi>Mons,</hi> a Hill, or Mountain, a
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Bern. in Serm.</hi> 29. <hi>Jan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen in Loc. Clarius in Loc. Engu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. in Loc. Jacob. Paniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cotus in Loc. Burgenſis</hi> 1. <hi>p. ſcrut.</hi> 4. <hi>diſt.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>Lorin in Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. Dr. Boys in Loc. Mollerus in Loc.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>non mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vendo,</hi> becauſe it ſhall never be ſhaken, or moved; <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.28, And then reſolves it, ſaying, he that walketh uprightly, &amp;c. where we have the moſt glorious evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, &amp; bleſſed properties of a
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Athanaſius in Lpiſt. de Interpr.</hi> Pſal.</note> Citizen of Heaven ſet down in order before us: They are 12.</p>
                  <p>The 1. is, <hi>He that walketh up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly.</hi> The word in the Hebrew is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> which, though it be uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rendred perfect; yet ſignifieth, not
<note n="*" place="margin">Melancthen in Loc.</note> one that is ſimply and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely ſo, and altogether free from ſin; for that is abſolutely denied <hi>Pro.</hi> 20.9. <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.2.1. <hi>John</hi> 1.9. but one that in his deſires &amp; pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes is without diſſimulation,
<note place="margin">1 Eviden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> and hypocriſie, and ſo walks up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly;
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:33158:57"/>as it is here rendred: where give me leave, becauſe this is the prime and chiefeſt Mark of a Citizen of Heaven to dwell a little while, and to ſhew you how this uprightneſs may be diſcerned, by theſe 3 proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>By a right aim;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Properties. of upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>By true deſires.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>By <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity.</hi>
                     <note n="1" place="margin">A Right Aim.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>By a right aim,</hi> for an up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right man doth in all things, aim at the glory of God; above all things, like <hi>David</hi> himſelf, (who hath penned this Pſalm, and here ſet down this property of up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.1. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Hypocrits, and ſuch as are not upright do all that they do to be ſeen of men, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.5.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. By true deſires,
<note n="2" place="margin">True De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires.</note> after Chriſt and grace, I mean, which are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivalent with deeds, as when <hi>Abraham</hi> had but a deſire, and
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:33158:57"/>purpoſe to pleaſe God, and to obey his command; it was taken for the deed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.16, 17. Read the place.</p>
                  <p>And the truth of ſuch deſires may be known again by 3 marks.
<note place="margin">3 Marks of true Deſires.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. True deſires are flaming, and fervent, called hungring and thirſting, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.6. pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and breathing, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. for look, as the Hart, having ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Serpents, and being there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by moſt mightily inflamed, and put into a grievous heat, pank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and panteth after Rivers of water to quench his thirſt, ſo do true deſires which are flaming and come from a fervent ſpirit, even long and thirſt after the things deſired; whether it be Chriſt, or grace, or faith, in a moſt vehement meaſure, and manner.</p>
                  <p>One writes of a gracious wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;
<note place="margin">Bolton.</note> that being aſked in her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gony, as ſhe was complaining of
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:33158:58"/>the want of Chriſt, and Grace, and Faith; but doth not your heart deſire, and long after Chriſt? Anſwered and ſaid; O yes, I have an Huſband, and Children, and many other comforts; but I would give them all, and all the good I ſhall ever ſee in this world, or in the world to come, to have my poor, thirſty Soul re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed with that precious blood of his, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. True and upright deſires are ever enterwoven with a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and holy uſe of all ſuch means, as may procure the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the things deſired; as faſting, praying, hearing, reading, ſelling of all, and the like. See <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.9. how deſires are fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by ſeeking after God.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. They are growing from lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to more, I mean more actions, from more to much more; from much more to habit, from habit
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:33158:58"/>to ſome competent perfection &amp; bigneſs in Chriſt. See, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. how deſires and growing are conjoyned, and look upon <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.21. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.3. and try your ſelves often by theſe 3 ſignes of true deſires; for if you have them, you have the graces which you deſire to have, and ſo muſt needs be aſſured of your Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I ſpeak after famous Mr. <hi>Rogers</hi> of <hi>Dedham;</hi> who hath converted ſo many Souls, his words are in his Doctrine of faith. c. 2. p. 128. <hi>What graces thou deſireſt, and conſtantly uſeſt the means to attain,</hi> thou haſt. Thus he.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi>
                     <note n="3" place="margin">Uniformity.</note> an upright and ſincere walker ſtriveth, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to be the ſame in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and at all times, like true Gold, which is the ſame in dirt, and when it is trodden upon, that it is when it is lifted up on
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:33158:59"/>high; and worn in a Ring, or Crown, it ſhineth whereſoever it is put: ſo he is the ſame in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, as well as in proſperity; among filthy livers, as well as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Saints; in bad company, as well as in good; at home as well as abroad; and like <hi>Ariſtotle's homo</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> he is, caſt him this way, and that away, and try him every way, and you ſhall find him right, and ſquare, in evil times as well as in good times; For he knoweth, that to be good at all times, and in all places, is but a Chriſtian's duty; but to be good in evil times, and among evil men, is an upright man's glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and to be blameleſs among a wicked and crooked Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yea, to the very credit of Religon, and Garland of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity; and ſo lobours to be like a Rock unmoveable; as he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to be, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.58. See
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:33158:59"/>alſo, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.3. <hi>his leaf alſo ſhall not wither,</hi> underſtand with any weather, and <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.9. where the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> Hebrew is, <hi>and Noah wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked indeſinently with God;</hi> though the world was bad, yet he was good, nay, as
<note n="*" place="margin">Chryſoſt. in Gen.</note> 
                     <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſpeaks of him, like a ſpark he was in the midſt of the Sea, which all that wickedneſs which did overſlow the whole earth could not quench. Whereas Hypocrites, and ſuch as want this uprightneſs are like Alcumy, which looketh like Gold, but proves not ſo; for when it is tryed; appears to be but counterfeit Gold: ſo they ſeem to be good, becauſe of ſome gliſtering ſhewes which they make by their profeſſion, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and performances, but when they are tryed, and faln into ſome Company or meet with op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; they prove falſe, and appear to be but counterfeits.
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:33158:60"/>And like the fiſh
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ambros</hi> in <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>exaem.</hi> l. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>Polypus</hi> which changeth colours, with every kind of ſtone it meets with in the Sea; ſo they in the Sea of this world ſhift and change their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, according to the place where they are, and the company into which they come; among the good, they will ſeem to be good, and talk as if they were good; yea, pray as if they were Saints; but among the bad, they are all as bad; ſo they will talk, and ſo they will do, and walk; abroad they will be like Angels, ſo they will behave themſelves, and ſo pure and heavenly they will ſeem to be, and ſo they will ſpeak, and pray very admirably; and as it were, with the Tongues of Angels; but follow them home, and you will ſee them car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry themſelves as if they were Devils; ſo they will lie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and be proud, and envious, and ſpight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:33158:60"/>and ſo ſome of them will roar, and tear, and rave, and ſtamp, and be contentious and unclean, and when it comes to family Duties, they will ſcarce pray at all ſome of them, or read, or have a ſavory ſpeech come out of their mouths all the day long; or if it happen that they do pray ſome of them, as brief, and could, and dry as may be, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly but a Repetition of the ſame things which they are ſtill wont to have in their domeſtick Devotions; and a kind of
<note n="*" place="margin">I ſpeak a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critical forms and repetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.7. &amp; not againſt all ſorms, and repetitions.</note> form, and how can it be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, ſeeing they have but a form of godlineſs; denying the power thereof? 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. But I have done with uprightneſs, but I hope you have not done with it, for it is the chief mark of all <hi>David</hi>'s marks; and it will, if you can find it, yeild you as much Aſſurance as any. I know the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:33158:61"/>man, ſaith Bleſſed <hi>Hooker,</hi> he is yet alive, that in extremity of horror of heart, ſaid, he had ſinned againſt the Holy Ghoſt; and therefore would have made away himſelf; but now that which kept him, was, his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence told him, that at ſuch a time his heart was upright before God, and that reſtrained him; &amp; God after that bleſſed him with aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of his love, and favour; &amp; therefore this uprightneſs; oh! this uprightneſs, what a mark it is? O try your ſelves daily by it. But I ſee that I have tranſgreſſed by my prolixity; I humbly crave pardon, and promiſe to be brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er hereafter,</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <note n="2" place="margin">Evidence.</note> 
                     <hi>He worketh Righteouſneſs.</hi> Righteouſneſs i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> his trade, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he trades for Heaven, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring to give to God what is Gods, and to Man what is Mans, and to every man his due.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <note n="3" place="margin">Evidence.</note> 
                     <hi>He ſpeaketh the truth in his
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:33158:61"/>heart.</hi> Another man may ſpeak truth too, but he ſpeaketh it not from his heart; becauſe it is not in his heart, but commonly ſuch as are none of Heavens Citizens will lie for advantage. It is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to them all inaſmuch as that they are called lyars. And <hi>ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Children, Iſa.</hi> 30.19. becauſe
<note n="*" place="margin">As <hi>Rabby Moyſes, l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 30.</note> uſed to them, and not uſed to ſpeak truth; whereas God's Children are called Children that will not lie, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.9.
<note n="4" place="margin">Evidence.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>He backbiteth not with his tongue;</hi> His tongue knoweth how to ſpeak well, but it know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not how to ſpeak ill,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.23.</note> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of any man; For it hath not ſo learned Chriſt, * who when he was reviled, reviled not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; whereas ſome will do lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle elſe, but revile, and ſlander, and backbite, and ſpeak evil of other men, who many times are better than themſelves.</p>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:33158:62"/>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>He doth no evil to his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,</hi>
                     <note n="5" place="margin">Evidence.</note> if he can do him good he will, hurt him he dares not, in his body, goods, or goodname; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ſome will be good to no body, but themſelves, and ſcarce them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as they ought, but they will wrong any one to get by it.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. <hi>He takes up no reproach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his neighbour,</hi>
                     <note n="6" place="margin">Evidence.</note> v. 3. for his charity will not ſuffer him which hopes better, becauſe it
<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 13.7.</note> hopeth all things.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. <hi>He is one in whoſe eies a vile perſon is contemned,</hi>
                     <note n="7" place="margin">Evidence.</note> v. 4. But how? it is not his Brother, (for ſo is even a vile perſon) but his Brothers faſhions and vile cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which he hates, and for which by him he is ſo ſcorned, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed; again, he contemns him not as he is a man, but as he is a vile man.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. <hi>He honoureth them that fear the Lord.</hi>
                     <note n="8" place="margin">Evidence.</note> I have read of a certain gracious King, called <hi>Jugo,</hi> King
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:33158:62"/>of the <hi>Dranes,</hi> that once he made a great feaſt, and placed his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and Lords in his Hall; but the poor Chriſtians which alſo were ſome of his gueſts, in a ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly higher Room, and kept them company; and when his Nobles repined, and wondred at it, he ſaid, theſe poor. Chriſtians I look upon, as thoſe that will reign with me as fellow Kings, and ſuch as will be my Companions in that other world; and therefore I place them and uſe them ſo. So highly he honoured them that feared the Lord; and ſo doth every Citizen of Heaven, where note, that this eſteem goeth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with love, as you may ſee, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.13. <hi>to eſteem them very highly in love;</hi> concerning which love, you know what is ſaid, <hi>We know that we have paſſed from death to life, becauſe we love the Brethren,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.14.
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:33158:63"/>which once ſo ſatisfied a gracious woman, that when ſhe could find no other mark but this, this did gain her the Aſſurance of her ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, becauſe her heart told her that ſhe loved the Brethren from the bottom of her heart.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. <hi>He ſweareth to his own hurt, and changeth not,
<note n="9" place="margin">Evidence.</note> v.</hi> 4. He is a man of his word, what he ſwears or promiſes ſhall ſtand, becauſe he knoweth that elſe he cannot ſtand, whether he win by it or loſe he careth not; though it be to my utter undoing, ſaith he, it matters not, if I may but go to Heaven at laſt, it ſhall not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble me much, though I muſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go all that I have upon earth firſt.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. <hi>He doth not put his money upon <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,
<note n="10" place="margin">Evidence.</note> v.</hi> 5. And what is Uſury? It is not only intereſt of a due quantity, as
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſura defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> intereſſe quantitat is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>Civilians</hi> define it; but the loan of a thing
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:33158:63"/>that may be
<note n="*" place="margin">De <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſur. 22.</note> conſumed in the uſe thereof, upon a compact for encreaſe; where note, that a man may commit it, whether he lend ſo to the rich or to the poor, the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Tho. Aqu.</hi> 2.2. q. 79. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> Hebrew calls it biting, becauſe it alwaies bites, either actually, or potentially, ſee <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.19. <hi>Thou ſhalt not lend upon <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury to thy Brother, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury of money, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury of victuals, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury of any thing that's lent upon <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> which muſt be underſtood thus, and which may be conſumed in the uſe thereof. Here obſerve how generally God ſpeaketh, not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting at all, him that is rich, but ſaying, to thy Brother. Now is not the rich thy Brother as well as the poor. I did preach once 16 Sermons againſt Uſury, as near as I can remember, upon this Pſalm, but now I muſt be very brief, becauſe I have promiſed brevity.</p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">So that for 1500 years after Chriſt, not any one of all the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and other holy Writers have ſtood for it. See <hi>Rob. Bolton</hi> againſt <hi>M. S. P.</hi> 5.</note>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:33158:64"/>
                  <p n="11">11. <hi>He taketh no reward againſt the innocent,</hi>
                     <note n="11" place="margin">Evidence.</note> v. 5. He is an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to bribery, becauſe God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it, and becauſe it blinds mens eies; and therefore whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be a Judge or Juſtice, or Lawyer, or Miniſter, or Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner, or Arbitrator, and ender of differences; he will rather beg from door to door, and from man to man, than be a falſe and bribe taking man.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. <hi>He doth,</hi>
                     <note n="12" place="margin">Evidence.</note> that is, labours to do <hi>all that is required to be done h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re,</hi> and elſe where, conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially; I ſay all, for we have a Rule in the School, that an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definite propoſition in a neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry matter is equivalent to an u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal, and ſuch a propoſition is this, <hi>Ergo.</hi> And beſides, by this All, the cloſe of this Pſalm, and this laſt mark doth ſweetly ſymphonize with the beginning of it, &amp; with the firſt, for the firſt
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:33158:64"/>maketh him in a manner perfect, becauſe the word for uprightneſs is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> which ſignifieth perfect, namely in the ſenſe foreſhewn. So that a Citizen of Heaven is truly a Catholick, a man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat in Chriſt, a general trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der into all the veſtigaes of God's Saints, like <hi>Zachary and Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, who walked in all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments and Ordinances of the Lord blameleſs, Luk.</hi> 1.16. and one that would not willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly omit, or neglect any one duty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>joyned by God, any one fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to be performed to God, any good turn to be done for God; no, not for a world, nor live in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one known ſin with allowance, becauſe he knoweth that if he ſhould, he would never be able to hold up his head with joy, nor have any confidence at all, that Heaven he ſhall have after all. That makes him to be ſo for all,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:33158:65"/>even all that is to be done, I add and conſequentially to do it with his All. All the powers of my Soul, and all the members of my Body, and all the moments and minutes of my time (ſaith he) ſhall go and be for God, for Chriſt, for Heaven; Heaven at laſt, and the Aſſurance of it will pay for all; <hi>and then I ſhall not be
<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 119.6.</note> aſhamed neither, whileſt I am here, when I ſhall have reſpect to all the Lord's Commandments:</hi> For this is the confidence that I ſhall have, that Heaven hereafte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> I ſhall have; where drinking at the ciſtern of life. I ſhall take my fill of the waters of life &amp; foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of pleaſures ſtreaming from <hi>Jehovah</hi>'s face, bleſſed for ever. Now my Brethren, ſhall I entreat and exhort you after all this, to try your ſelves by theſe never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>failing Evidences; even daily to be aſſured that you ſhall inhabit
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:33158:65"/>with God, that holy hill above everlaſtingly. I believe it is a thing which ſome of you never did. For men think it to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough if they try themſelves then, when ſigns and marks are delivered in ſome certain Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; Nay, ſome will not try themſelves then, and therefore no wonder that ſuch as are aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of their ſalvation, are like
<note n="*" place="margin">Rara avis in terris.</note> Turtles very rare; and ſhall I not for that cauſe perſwade you as earneſtly as I may, to take this new courſe of trying your ſelves; ſo every day hereafter to gain the Aſſurance of the ſalvation of your Souls. O Souls, in the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of Chriſt Jeſus, I beſeech you that you will be perſwaded, and no longer neglect ſo great ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I ſhould ſay, the gaining of the Aſſurance of ſo great ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>But ſhall I pray to God for you
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:33158:66" rendition="simple:additions"/>too? By God's help I will, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Lord bleſs theſe my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to you, and bleſs you. He grant that theſe very evidences may not only lie before ye in this Book, but alſo to you in your hearts. He minde you of them, becauſe elſe ſome daies you will neglect them; that ſo you may come to be aſſured daily, that you ſhall manſion with his holy ſelf, in that holy Hill it ſelf, which is ſo far beyond all other Hills, and high Mountains in this world, moſt certainly, and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly. So be it.</p>
                  <p>But,
<note place="margin">A Caſe of Conſcience.</note> here I muſt reſolve a great caſe of conſcience. For ſome will he ready to ſay; Sir<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we have uſed ſuch means as theſe, and yet cannot gain this Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; and therefore what ſhall we do in this caſe?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwered. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>I Anſwer,</hi>
 There is a two-fold Aſſurance.</p>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:33158:66"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Aſſurance of Evidence.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Aſſurance of Adherence.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>The Aſſurance of Evidence;</hi> when with bleſſed <hi>Stephen,</hi> we ſee Heaven as it were open, and the Son of man in it, that is, when we ſee the ſplendor of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, when his countenance is lifted up upon us, and in us; when in us for the preſent is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Heaven; when Heaven is poured out upon our ſouls; when our ſouls are enroabed with the garment of ſalvation; when ſalvation crowns us, fills us, ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows us; when we can ſee nothing, taſt nothing, feel nothing but Heaven, and muſt ſay as <hi>Jacob, This is none other but the houſe of God, and this the gate of Heaven, Gen.</hi> 28.17.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Of Adherence.</hi> As when we can ſee no ſuch thing, when eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing goes againſt us, when God frowns, Chriſt withdraweth,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:33158:67"/>the Spirit chides; when if we look up, we can behold nothing but wrath, even the wrath of a ſin-revenging God; if about us, nothing but horrour; if within us, nothing but deſpair; if under us, nothing but Hell, and yet can ſay as <hi>Job, though he ſlay me, yet will I truſt in him, Job</hi> 13.15. Now, when the firſt Aſſurance cannot for the preſent by any means be had, we muſt ſtick to the ſecond, we have a notable place for it, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.10. <hi>Who is among you that feareth the Lord, that obeyeth the voice of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi> (and ſo doth, what here hath been ſpoken as from the Lord, by his ſervant) <hi>that walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in darkneſs? let him truſt in the name of the Lord, and ſtay upon his God.</hi> The Hebrew is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>? whence is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> a ſtaff, to ſhew that a man in darkneſs goeth by a ſtaff, ſuſtaining himſelf by it, to
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:33158:67"/>keep himſelf up; ſo ſuch a one muſt reſt himſelf upon God in this his dark and diſmal eſtate to be kept up. See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.4. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this ſtaff; and let me ſay unto you yet farther, let ſuch a one cloath himſelf with patience, and never think himſelf the more
<note n="*" place="margin">For he may be more ſafe than he who feels the ſweetneſs of joy, and may be lifted up with it, ſaith <hi>Gerſon.</hi>
                     </note> unſafe, let him centre himſelf in Chriſt, let him wrap up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in his merits; let him ſay, here I will live, and here I will die: If I periſh, I periſh, (as
<note n="*" place="margin">Eſthe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.16.</note> 
                     <hi>Eſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her</hi> ſaid once) it is all one, but it ſhall be upon this
<note n="*" place="margin">So <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> tels us.</note> ſtaff which I will not let go, but keep to my grave whither I go. As for the other of Evidence, ye will, or may, in that alſo before you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, and ceaſe to be retainers to the Sun, ſun yourſelves, and have your part.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <note n="2" place="margin">Incentives of a ſorts.</note> Now Incentives; and</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Let me deduce ſome from the evils that will follow, if you
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:33158:68"/>will not follow theſe directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Others from the good that will come, if you will come to labour for this Aſſurance.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>As for the evils. You will live</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>In continual doubts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>In continual fears, and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>You will live in continual doubts,</hi> and queſtion even every thing, as whether. ye did not all that ever ye did in Hypocriſie; &amp; whether your love be true, your converſion true, your godlineſs true; and eſpecially you will doubt of your Faith, whether that be true ſaving Faith,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Nam fidel is non eſt, niſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> qui ſuae ſalutis ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitati in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nixus Diabolo &amp; morti confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denter inſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet quomo do doceinur,</hi> Rom. 8.38. <hi>Calv. Inſt. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>ſ.</hi> 16.</note> yea, or no, becauſe ſo few have it, and becauſe ſo much temporary and hypocritical Faith is going; where give me leave to dwell a little while, becauſe I hear moſt doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtians call their Faith moſtly in queſtion. And becauſe
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:33158:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>thoſe two kinds of Faith carry men ſo far as they do, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by raiſe ſuch doubts. As<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Temporary carry men ſo far as to make them hear the word, even with j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y, <hi>Luke</hi> 8.13. Oh! me-thought, ſaith the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary, I was even raviſhed when I heard ſuch a Sermon.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It maketh men to be not hearers only, but doers alſo of many things, both in their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies and apart, even to admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Mark<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> 6.20.</p>
                  <p>St. <hi>Baſil</hi> knew ſuch a Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Baſil Epiſt. mihi p.</hi> 515.</note> who for a time lived ſo ſtrictly, as that he did e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven admire him; for he had faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo often as that he had brought himſelf to nothing almoſt, but ſkin and bones, and counted the greateſt wealth as dung, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered his cheeks with rivers of tears, and walked as he thought with God day and night; in brief,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:33158:69"/>lived ſo ſolitarily, and retired<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as if he had cared for no earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly creature; and yet at laſt fell not only off, but alſo in love with a ſtrange woman, having forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken his own wife, and I do not read in the ſame <hi>Baſil</hi> of his reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verie at all; and this and the like examples cannot but make any man who wants this Aſſurance, to tremble, and doubt. So the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritical, I mean the ſturdie Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites faith,
<note n="*" place="margin">Famous Mr. <hi>Hooker.</hi>
                     </note> as Divines call it, Good Lord! how far it car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth?</p>
                  <p n="1">1. It brings him to a great deal of ſorrow, being
<note n="*" place="margin">Matt. 13.22.</note> thorny ground, and having his thorns in him, that is, pricking ſorrows, and troubles of mind; The Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary, ſaith he, is deceived; for he came eaſily by his faith; he was never much troubled before it, or about it; he believed by and by, but mine coſt me dear;
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:33158:69"/>and the truth is, ſuch a Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite commonly hath ſorrow e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for the quantitie of it, though not enough for the quality or uprightneſs, becauſe everie valley is not filled, according to <hi>Luke</hi> 3.5. though he himſelf, like a high Mountain, was thrown &amp; caſt down by a ſoul-piercing Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, there being a hollow falſe heart left in him.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It makes him even to trade with Chriſt, and that much too, like that
<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 19.16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22.</note> young man who alſo was ſo ſorrowful, and had ſo much talk with Chriſt about his ſalvation; and made as if he would do much by Chriſt's per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, though not to the loſing hand upon any terms, but only ſo far, and to ſo much as will ſuit with his eſtate and occaſions.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Nay, it will carry him out e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto ſuffering; for ſaith he, the Temporarie cozeneth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:33158:70"/>for he is
<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 13.21.</note> offended &amp; yields, and
<note n="‖" place="margin">
                        <hi>De quo</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates, l. 3. c. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Ezebolius</hi>-like complies by and by,
<note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 8.13.</note> and is gone; but I ſcorn to do ſo, I will ſtand it out to the laſt, though I die for it. See 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.3. how a man may give his bodie to be burnt, and yet want Charitie; and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently true ſaving faith, <hi>which works by love, Gal.</hi> 5.6. Beloved, there is a Rule in Logick. Thoſe disjunct Propoſitions, both parts whereof are true, the whole muſt needs be true; if either part be falſe, then the Propoſition muſt be falſe. Now here both parts are true, I may give my bodie to be burnt, and yet want Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie; ſo a man may ſuffer, and yet want faith, <hi>Ergo.</hi> For there be many things in mans heart that he will rather die than yield, as Pride, Obſtinacie, ſelf-wildneſs, ſturdineſs, and the like: This, this maketh men doubt ſo; and
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:33158:70"/>doubt they will, till by the uſe of means formerly preſcribed, they gain that Aſſurance which is here required: and therefore get it, O, by all mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> get it, my dearly beloved; for, how long will ye doubt ſo?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. You will live in continual fear and heavineſs; for you are whilſt you want this Aſſurance in darkneſs, and ſee no light, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.10. the Hebrew is brightneſs, which is more than light, and ſeemeth to allude to the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God's countenance, which a child of God walking in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and wanting this Aſſurance, cannot ſee. Now when a man walketh in darkneſs, you know what a ſad fearful man he is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he can ſee no light; every man that he meets he takes to be an enemie; everie voice he hears he thinks to be the voice of Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; everie ſtep he makes, he
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:33158:71"/>fears will make him fall: ſo, when men are not aſſured of their ſalvation; and of God's fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, how ſad and fearful are they? everie Scripture almoſt they meet with they take to be againſt them; everie ſtep of theirs to be a ſtep into hell; everie glimpſe of comfort to be a delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Devil; and ſo they live the ſorrowfulleſt, the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malleſt, the diſconſolateſt life that poor creatures can live, liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a continual fear of death, of Devils, and of hell fire, which burns for ever. It hath been my own caſe when I wanted this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance; I was afraid to be alone, and afraid of Satan, becauſe of his buffetings, and ſo will you be, or are alreadie. O my brethren, the tongue of man is hardly able to expreſs the ſorrow, the fear, the perplexity that a poor doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:33158:71"/>Chriſtian is in whilſt he wants this Aſſurance, and cannot ſee the light of the Lord's counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; when he looks upon his Wife, (if he have any) his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, his Goods, wherein others take a world of comfort, he ſaith, what comfort can I take in them who cannot be aſſured at all, as others are, of the favour of God, which is better than ten wives, ten ſons, nay, 10 thouſand worlds? when he looks upon his meat and drink, he ſaith, what good can all this good meat &amp; ſweet drink do to me, who have no aſſurance at all that ever I ſhall ſit down with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and drink of that new &amp; ſweeteſt wine which they drink of in the Kingdom of God? When he looks upon his bodie, he ſaith; O, how will this bodie of mine be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to dwell in that flaming fire? and how, O how will it be able
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:33158:72"/>to indure thoſe * everlaſting burnings? When he thinks up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his ſoul, he ſaith, O my poor
<note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 33.14.</note> trembling ſoul, whether wilt thou go, when thou goeſt hence? to Heaven or Hell? I know not, God knows; or thus:
<note n="*" place="margin">As that great Emperor <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mula Vagula Blandula.</hi>
                     </note> anxiviouſly I have li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, doubtfully ſhall I die, not knowing whether I ſhall go; as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaid, that great Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher; or as <hi>David,</hi> that great King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.15. ſaid of <hi>Abſalom</hi> his Son once; ſo ſaith he of his ſoul, with a little change; O my ſoul, would to God; I did know what would become of thee after me; but I know it not, and therefore O ſad man that I am, and O ſad ſoul that thou art, Oh! my ſoul, my ſoul; Oh! how ſhould this prick ye on there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore like a Spur, to the getting of that here required, Aſſurance of the ſalvation of your ſouls.</p>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:33158:72"/>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Some Incentives I ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce from the good that will come,
<note n="2" place="margin">Sort of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centives.</note> if you will come to labour for this Aſſurance:</hi> as,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Look as they that are ſure of their vocation and election, ſo they that are ſure of their ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; by a neceſſary conſequence ſhall not be barren in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, in 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8. know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge a man may have, though no aſſurance of his ſalvation he have. As good a Logician he may be as ever was <hi>Auſtin,</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Auguſtinus <hi>à petitiono vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabatur diale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticus.</hi>
                     </note> who for it was called the Dialectick; ſpeak he may diverſe tongues, as He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew, Greek, Latine, &amp;c. nay, as many as <hi>Genusbrey Sultan, Soly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>'s Interpreter, 15 Languages, or as <hi>Mithridates</hi> 22, as the French Academy hath it. An <hi>Oxford</hi> of learning, a walking Library, an ocean of wit, he may
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:33158:73"/>be; abilities he may have to wade into the Abyſs of the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of God, and to interpret my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries; a dexterity he may have with the piercing key of his moſt excellent knowledge, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock the golden cabinet of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel ſecrets; parts he may have with the far ſeeing eie of his large underſtanding, to penetrate the occult qualities of nature; able he may be to diſcover what is in the bowels of the earth, in the bottom of the ſeas, in the heights of mountains; nay, he may with the wings of his profound learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing even ſore up to that flaming hill above, where the ſtars are, yea, beyond the <hi>Caſtiopeia</hi> it ſelf, and be able to diſcourſe of the altitude, magnitude, natures, influences of thoſe glorious lights which are in that ſpangled ſkie, even to admiration; but as bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren he will be for want of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:33158:73"/>and goodneſs, if he want the the Aſſurance of his election, of ſalvation, as the mountain of <hi>Gilboa,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.21. Contrarily, if he be ſure of that, then, oh how fruitful will he be then in all manner of holineſs, and godly converſation? and how, oh how will that even fill his ſails, with life, with motion, with action, and make him navigate even with expanſed ſails, through ſeas of duties? For, what, oh! what will not a man do for God, when once he is certain of the favour of God? Oh! how he will pray, faſt, read, meditate, love, when once he is perſwaded of his love? and therefore who is there among all this people that fain would grow in grace, and not be barren in knowledge? let him labour for the aſſurance of his ſalvation, and he ſhall have his hearts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire. O my God, fulfil thou the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:33158:74"/>deſire of that ſoul, I humbly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and beſeech thee with my very ſoul.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>You ſhall never fall,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. nor look back, like <hi>Lot</hi>'s wife, which for it was turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Pillar of Salt; yet to be ſeen, ſaith <hi>Tertullian,</hi> to ſeaſon ſuch as fall. Now, you do nothing almoſt but fall, as being in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.10. now into the ſin of pride, then of paſſion, then of luxurie; now ye are too jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial, then too fantaſtical, in your gates, cloaths; now too light, then too melancholick; now ye talk too much, then too little; now ye ſell too dear, then ye uſe falſe weight, or mix your wares bad with good, ſome of you: now ye are too ſtrange, then too familiar, too wanton, ſome of ye; now as high as <hi>Lucifer</hi> for pride, then as low as <hi>Demas</hi> for world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs; for even in our time are
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Tertul. in Sodom. Carm.</hi> p. 646.</note>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Aug. in Pſ.</hi> 77. p. 830.</note>
                     <pb n="129" facs="tcp:33158:74"/>many <hi>Demaſes.</hi> The world is now as it was formerly; there was none then, but there hath been, or is ſome one now that parallels him, and is, as it were, his revived ſelf. But let a man get the Aſſurance of his ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; let him ſun himſelf in the light of God's countenance; let him be crowned with the certain hope of glorie; let him be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh'd once with the over-flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtreams of divine conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Let God's Spirit once ſpeak peace to his ſpirit, and he will ſay; O, I would not be as I have been, nor do as I have done, no, not for a thouſand worlds; I was proud, paſſionate, envious, laſcivious, covetous, as others are, but I would not be ſo again, if one would give me all the wealth of <hi>England.</hi> Oh! how much ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is the aſſurance of my ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, than all the pleaſures of ſin
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:33158:75"/>for a ſeaſon; or thus, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſaid to his Miſtreſs, being enticed by her, <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.9. <hi>My Maſter hath kept nothing from me, but thee, becauſe thou art his Wife, How then can I do this great wickedneſs and ſin againſt God?</hi> ſo ſaith he when he is enticed by ſin; My Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath kept nothing from me but his glory, which, he ſaith, he will give to none other;
<note place="margin">Iſa. 42.8.</note> He hath put ſuch joy in my heart, ſuch light into my mind, ſuch aſſurance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my ſoul, as that I am even ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed with him in my ſoul; and therefore how can I commit this wickedneſs, and ſin againſt my God? Oh! I will not do it for the whole world.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>You will thereby enter Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven:</hi> this alſo follows by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence from the enſuring of our calling and election; for, he that is ſure of the one muſt needs
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:33158:75"/>be ſure of the other alſo, as I ſhewed
<note n="*" place="margin">From <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29, 30.</note> formerly. Now, what ſaith <hi>Peter? Give diligence to make your calling and election ſure,</hi> 2 <hi>ch.</hi> 1.10. and then <hi>v.</hi> 11. <hi>For ſo an entrance ſhall be mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred unto, abundantly into the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> which words may be underſtood, not only of an entrance to be mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred hereafter, but alſo miniſtred now, when we are made ſure of Heaven, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16. when we are ſaved by hope, when namely Jeſus Chriſt is pleas'd to ſhine up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us with the light of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, beaming into our hearts;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Quae eſt luae, quae irradiat cor meum.</hi> Aug. <hi>in Med.</hi>
                     </note> when our hearts do leap for joy; when joy triumphs over ſorrow; when ſorrow is turned into ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; when rivers of comfort are ſhed and ſhowred down from the Throne of Grace upon our ſouls; when our ſouls feed on
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:33158:76"/>
                     <hi>Ambroſian</hi> dainties, then are we entred into the Kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, which then is in us, as well as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove us, and conſiſts in <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and peace, and joy in the Holy-Ghoſt, Rom.</hi> 14.17. and therefore if now as well as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after you would live as it were in Heaven, then get the Aſſurance of Heaven, then beg it, then ſeek after it, by the means ſhewn for it, and never be at reſt, till ye be ſo bleſt; for then, oh the extati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call leaps of your rejoycing hearts! oh the dancings of your gladded ſpirits! oh the gloryings of your rav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſhed ſouls! which then you will be able to tell of, ſaying; O what a Heaven did I feel in me, when my Beloved ſpake to me, and aſſured me that my poor ſoul ſhould be ſaved undoubtedly! Oh, how ſweet was that voice, that word, that
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:33158:76"/>ſaying to my ſoul! O how was my ſoul then even heavened in God, emboſomed in Chriſt, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatized in the Spirit, and eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the higheſt horizon of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine conſolation! To ſay no more, this entrance gotten by Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance is the ſweeteſt, the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſeſt, the pleaſanteſt thing that ever beatified and warmed the heart of man upon earth; for a very Paradiſe it is, and a Heaven upon earth; wherein I now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to leave you upon earth, and therefore I do ſo preſs it, to make you preſs for it, that you may gain it; beſeeching you by the mercies of God, that you will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all this, ſadly and ſeriouſly conſider all this, and remember the ſad condition wherein you formerly lived, living in doubts; and that if you love your ſouls, you will now even heaven your ſelves upon earth, enſouling your
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:33158:77"/>ſelves in God, ſunning your ſelves in Chriſt, and emparadi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing your ſelves in that ever, and over-glorious Aſſurance of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, which I have ſo urged by believing, and thoſe other bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed means which have been fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhewn; ſhewing your ſelves to be not hearers only, but doers alſo, and ſuch doers as are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citated by the Word, ſuſcitated by the Spirit, animated with heat of zeal, elevated with height of hope, and even ready to ſoar up upon the wings of confidence, and joy, beyond that flaming hill where the ſtars are, and to enter that holy hill above, where ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of joy is unutterable, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility bleſſed, immortality im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, felicity to be enjoyed thorow all eternity.</p>
                  <closer>To God alone be all praiſe, laud, and glory.</closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33158:77"/>
                  <p>Fifteen Soul-ſolacing CONFERENCES WITH CHRIST, Touching Sins and the World's Conqueſt by Faith: Making uſe of the joys of Heaven, and of Chriſt's ſweeteſt Promiſes, Love, Death, Offices, Interceſſion, and overcoming the World, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>According to the High and Noble Art of fighting the great fight of Faith, <bibl>1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.12.</bibl>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fitted for all ſuch gracious Souls, as do moſt heartily defire to ſee the death of their ſtrong and mighty Corruptions, and a thorow Conqueſt of this vile and troubleſom World.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>Chriſtopher Jelinger,</hi> M. A.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the year, 1664.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="conference">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33158:78"/>
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:33158:78"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The firſt Conference: Tending to the right happy ſubduing of ſin, by the Word of Promiſe,</hi> Mich. 7.19.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believer.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 42.11.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hy art thou caſt down O my ſoul? why art thou ſo diſquieted within me?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> Diſquieted within me, ſay ye? Nay, wonder that I am not even overwhelmed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> What is the matter?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> Ah! ſin, ſin,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 38.3, 4, 6.</note> which is as an heavie burthen, even too hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie for me to bear, it makes me grieve all the day long.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> I do not blame thee, O my ſoul, that thou art troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:33158:79"/>&amp; takeſt on for ſin. <hi>For
<note n="*" place="margin">a Cor. 7.10.</note> godly ſorrow worketh repentance to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,
<note n="*" place="margin">Poſſidon, in Vit. Aug. c. 27. attribuit haec verba Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>br.</note> not to be repented of:</hi> but thou grieveſt too much, as if thou wer'ſt without hope, whereas thou ſerveſt a good and a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lord, who pittieth them that are his, <hi>as a
<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.12, 13.</note> Father pittieth his children, and removes our tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions from us, as far as the Eaſt is from the Weſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> I grant that God is very pittiful, but I doubt whether he will have mercy on me, becauſe it is written
<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 28.13.</note> 
                     <hi>who ſo confeſſeth and forſaketh his ſins ſhall have mercy:</hi> but I am as full of ſin ſtill as the ground is full of piles of graſs, the ſea-ſhore full of ſands, and the Ocean full of drops of water, ſo that I cannot ſay that ſin is forſaken, and therefore I can expect no mercy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> No mercy? what doeſt thou then make of <hi>David,</hi> whoſe
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:33158:79"/>words but now were cited? did he not commit both murther and adultery, and yet thou ſeeſt he doth not forſake his own mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, though he was not able quite to forſake his own ſinful luſts.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> Will you compare your ſelf with <hi>David,</hi> who though he did fall grievouſly, commiting murther and adultery, yet was not full of adultery, for he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of that ſin, and of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alſo, and after that ye do not read that he fell ſo again: but I, your poor ſoul am (as I ſaid but now) full of ſin; even ſometimes full of envy, then of pride, then of luſts, and therefore I muſt needs be hopeleſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> Hopeleſs! I perceive O my Soul, that thou doeſt ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly forget and bury in oblivion the ſacred words, ſweeteſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> What conſolation?</p>
                  <pb n="140" facs="tcp:33158:80"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.
<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Tim. 1.15, 16.</note> That Jeſus Chriſt came into the world to ſave ſinners,</hi> of whom <hi>Paul</hi> was chief, who yet obtained mercy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> It ſhould ſeem you will compare your ſelf with <hi>Paul</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, who though he was bad be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his converſion, yet was not ſo afterward, for he tells us, that he was even
<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 6.14.</note> crucified to the world, and the world crucified to him; but you are not ſo dead to the world, for you take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, even too much pleaſure and joy in the things of this world, and are oft times mightily tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with the world and the faſhions of it, unto which ye do too much conform your ſelf, in your diet, apparel, diſcourſe; yea, and ye cannot deny, but ye are too eager in the purſuit of the profits and deceitful riches of this world, forgetting both what the firſt and beſt Chriſtians did
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:33158:80"/>before you, and what you ought to do after them, vilipending and deſpiſing all the worlds ſtately pomp, and fading glory, and therefore I am ſo perplexed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> I do not equal my ſelf with <hi>Paul,</hi> but only comfort thee, O my ſoul, with his example; for though I be not equally mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to this vile world with him, yet canſt not thou deny, but I do truly endeavour to be cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to the world, and I would have thee know that <hi>Paul</hi> was not an Angel neither, though an eminent Saint, but a ſinner, both before and after his converſion; an impenitent ſinner, I mean firſt, and a repentant ſinner after; for therefore he ſaith in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quoted place, <hi>Chriſt came to ſave ſinners, of whom I am chief:</hi> mark, I am, and not I have been, and again <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.15. <hi>that which I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low not I do:</hi> mark, do, and not I
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:33158:81"/>have done, and ver. 24. <hi>'O wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man that I am,</hi> Note again, I am, and not I have been, <hi>who ſhall deliver me from the body of this death?</hi> Mark, ſhall deliver me, and not hath delivered me, though that be a truth too, that he was in a great meaſure morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and partly delivered alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; and therefore be not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heartned, O my Soul, for though <hi>Paul</hi> was tranſcendently more crucified to the world than I, yet was he peſtred and troubled with a world of ſin, which he calls the body of death, as well as I; and his only hope and truſt was in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, that he would deliver him at laſt, for ſo he ſaith, <hi>I thank God through Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, and would you know what I mean to do in this heavy caſe? then I muſt tell you, that I will collocate and place my ſole and whole truſt
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:33158:81"/>and affiance in the Lord Chriſt, who as he hath delivered me in part, ſo doubtleſs will deliver me yet more and more, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as being certain of it that he will do it, I thank God for it thorow Chriſt who will do it, as if he had done it already, and this ſame courſe thou alſo muſt take, O my ſoul, and therefore <hi>hope thou in God, for I ſhall yet praiſe him who is the health of my countenance and my God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> But why is not that world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, which I objected but now, as diſcovering it ſelf ſo, by ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerneſs after and delightfulneſs in the things of this world, with its faſhions, at leaſt more ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed yet (all this while) than it is?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> Doeſt thou wonder at that, O my ſoul? then conſider, 1. What a multitude of enemies do continually aſſault me, I mean Satanical ſuggeſtions, the
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:33158:82"/>worlds enchanting provocations, and the fleſhes own inſurrections moſt mighty and moſt frequent, which maketh me even wonder how a poor ſoul can overcome ſuch a world in any meaſure; for who would not rather admire a little Ship, if fighting with many great &amp; well mann'd Turkiſh Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys, it ſhould eſcape though her maſt and all the higher part of it ſhould be beaten off down to the water, and many men ſlain in her, than enquire why it ſhould be ſo ſpoiled, debilitated and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? which is juſt thy caſe, O my ſoul; for thou haſt fought with many great and peſtilent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, like a little Ship, and yet didſt ſo far eſcape, as that they could not totally nor finally pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail againſt thee, though it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denied, but that they have waſted and ſpoiled, and hurt thee much, and killed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:33158:82"/>good motions, and therefore I ſay, that even this is a thing to be wondred at.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Beſides, God hath his time for every thing, a time for tryal and a time for help, and to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due the world in a greater mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as he will, and therefore
<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 42.11. for the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew is <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>expecta.</hi>
                     </note> wait thou upon God.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Again, it may be that the means were not ſo induſtriouſly uſed, whereby the world may be ſubdued, even the viſion and application of Faith, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us amend this fault, and then I hope all will be well.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> You ſay well, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore up and be doing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt.</hi> What manner of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications be theſe, which you have, being ſo
<note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 24.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, 18, 19.</note> ſad?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> Concerning ſin which my ſoul is troubled for, and would be delivered from.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Art thou. willing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:33158:83"/>O Chriſtian Soul, to part with any ſinful pleaſure, profit, honour, and with life it ſelf for my ſake?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 21.17.</note> Thou Lord knoweſt all things, thou knoweſt that I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it, and would not willingly live or lie in the practiſe of any
<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> one known ſin.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Luk, 24.25.</note> O fooliſh ſoul then, and ſlow to believe all that the Prophets have ſpoken; did deſt thou never read what is written,
<note n="*" place="margin">Mich. 7.19, 20.</note> 
                     <hi>he will have compaſſion upon us, he will ſubdue our iniquities, and thou will caſt all their ſins in the depth of the ſea?</hi> Mark, he will not only have compaſſion, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning iniquity, and paſſing by the tranſgreſſion of the remnant of his heritage, but alſo ſubdue your iniquities, that is, he will
<note n="*" place="margin">For the original is <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>ſubjugabit vi ac violentia capiet.</hi>
                     </note> ſubjugate and bring under the yoke, as it were, * all your ſins, ſo as that, like yoked oxen you
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:33158:83"/>ſhall be able to rule them, though in themſelves they be never ſo unruly, and he will even offer and infer violence unto your na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo as that your ſinful luſts, deſires, and affections ſhall be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven captivated in ſuch a manner, as that they ſhall not be able to range and to rage ſo freely as they did: and therefore truſt in God, O thou Chriſtian Soul, who is the health of thy countenance, and thy God, who can, and will help thee and deliver thee at laſt moſt happily out of all thy mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> Bleſſed be thou, ſweet Jeſus, dear Saviour, who thus art pleaſed to comfort me; and praiſed be thy holy name, in the which I ſweetly repoſe my truſt, for I know thee what thou art, The Holy one of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the mighty God, the Prince of peace, the God of comfort, even <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuel,</hi>
                     <pb n="158" facs="tcp:33158:84"/>God with us, who by this ſweet and precious promiſe art faſt bound to perform in me, what thou haſt here promiſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, and therefore, Lord, do un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me as thou canſt, and then I ſhall be able to forſake ſin as I would, I humbly beſeech thee; yea, I do even aſſure my ſelf, that as thou canſt, ſo thou wilt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou art the
<note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 14.6.</note> truth it ſelf, and therefore I ſay,
<note n="*" place="margin">Mich. 7.19, 20.</note> thou Lord wilt caſt all my ſins in the depth of the Sea of thy mercy, and ſuffocate them in thy precious blood, as the <hi>Egyptians</hi> were drowned in the Red-ſea; and wilt ſubdue them, as they were ſubdued, that they may not rule over me, as they did, when I lived in <hi>Egypt,</hi> the houſe of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, in the ſtate of my unrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neracy; I mean, O Lord, Lord, I believe that thou wilt perform thy truth to me, as well as to
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:33158:84"/>
                     <hi>Jacob,</hi> and thy mercy as to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> which thou haſt ſworn from the daies of old, as thou art God from everlaſting.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt.</hi> I ſee thou wilt hold me to my word, like <hi>Jacob,</hi> and the truth is, that being the truth, I cannot go from them, nor deny them, and therefore
<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 15.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> be it to thee as thou wilt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> Amen, Lord Jeſus.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="conference">
                  <head>The ſecond Conference: Wherein Faith makes uſe of the Promiſe of Heaven, and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Hell againſt ſin.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BEliev.</hi> Seeſt thou not, O my Soul, theſe ſnares, which Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan that cunning fowler hath laid for thee, to illaqueate and to catch thee?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> What ſnares?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> Snares of covetouſneſs,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:33158:85"/>in the goods of this world, ſnares of voluptuouſneſs in eating, drinking, marrying; ſnares of pride, in praying, preaching, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing, Almſ-giving, ſnares in ſleeping, ſnares in waking, and in every other thing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> I ſee them, I ſee them, but what muſt I do to eſcape them?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> Looking beyond them with the eie of Faith upon the word of truth in general, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the Word of Promiſe in ſpecial.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> But that is very large, and therefore how can I ſee it all, or appropriate it, when I am ſuddenly aſſaulted.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> nor is it neceſſary that one do make uſe of all at once, and therefore at this time chuſe but one threatning, and one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe; for inſtance, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13. <hi>If ye live after the fleſh ye ſhall die,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:33158:85"/>but if ye thorow the ſpirit do mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the deeds of the body, ye ſhall live;</hi> and then imagine 3 ſeveral habitations, a high, a low, a mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, the high is the Houſe of God called Heaven, the low Hell, the middle this world; the two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams are quite contrary one to the other, but the middle is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what like to both; for in it is light and darkneſs, heat and cold, ſickneſs and health, ſadneſs and gladneſs, hatred and love, good and bad, juſt and unjuſt, Lords and ſervants, rule and ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, death and life, whereof one part doth emblematize Heaven, the other Hell; for in this world there is a mixture of good and bad, but in Heaven are none bad, but all good, in Hell none good but all bad; and of the men of the world ſome are ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated and lifted up on high into Heaven, others are drawn and
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:33158:86"/>thrown down into Hell, for like and like are to be joined, good with good, bad with bad, juſt men with juſt Angels, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing men with Angels tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing; the ſervants of God with God; the ſervants of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan with Satan: Think on this O my ſoul, when thou ſeeſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans ſnares before thee, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve verily, that as living in the world thou ſeeſt the image and ſimilitude both of Heaven and Hell before thee, even light and darkneſs, life and death; ſo they which live after the fleſh, fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the luſts and doing the works of the fleſh ſhall never inherit the Kingdom of God, and that they which mortify and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them ſhall certainly be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paradiſed, &amp; tranſlated into that higheſt habitation and
<note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.1.</note> houſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal in the Heavens; where there is light without darkneſs,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:33158:86"/>health without ſickneſs, gladneſs without ſadneſs, love without hatred, good and juſt inhabitants only, and none bad, ſatiety and fulneſs even of joy and pleaſures without famine, and life with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out death, even life for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more; Doeſt thou believe this, O my ſoul?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> I do believe it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> Then conſider whether thou oughteſt not to avoid all the foreſaid ſnares; mortifying the fleſh, with all the luſts and affections therefore, that thou maieſt live and not die for ever.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> So I will by Gods help.</p>
                  <p>But you ſaid that I muſt apply alſo the word of promiſe in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial, what do ye mean by that?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> Thou muſt aſſure thy ſelf, that thou in particular ſhalt live forever, and be Angelized in caſe thou ſubdue and morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thy corrupt nature, and reſiſt
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:33158:87"/>Satans tyranny; look up there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, O my Soul, and poſſeſs thy ſelf, as it were of Heaven by faith, and thou ſhalt eaſily over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the earth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul,</hi> I do now underſtand you; &amp; therefore I lift up my ſelf as well as I am able, and behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, as it were, the place ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and prepared for me; I ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute it as the Patriarchs ſaluted
<note n="*" place="margin">Hebr. 11.13.</note> the promiſes, when by faith they ſaw them, ſaying; O <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, Jeruſalem,</hi> whoſe
<note n="*" place="margin">Revel. 21.21</note> ſtreets are of gold, and gates of pearls, how pleaſant and how beautiful art thou? Glorious things are ſpoken of thee, O thou City of God, for in thee there is nothing but light, and joy, and bliſs, and bleſſedneſs, and ſweetneſs, and comfort, and peace, and life, even life vital, life beatifical, life immortal, life eternal without ſpot, without dolor, without Anx<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:33158:87"/>without corruption, change or perturbation, O ſweet, O quiet, O bleſſed life! O life of lives! O life angelical! O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thee alſo, O new &amp; Heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> there is no adverſary to oppoſe; no ſin, to Intice; no fear, but love<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> no Night but only day; no Sun but inſtead of it the Son of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, the Son of righteouſneſs, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for ever. And therefore fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel all earthly Pleaſures, Profits, Honours. For they be but as dung and dirt, and ſhadows, and dreams in compariſon of that
<note n="*" place="margin">Hebr. 10.34:</note> induring ſubſtance, &amp; that
<note n="*" place="margin">2 Corinth. 4.17. Pſal. 16.11:</note> et ernal weight of glory, and thoſe ſurpaſſing pleaſures which are of the right hand of God for evermore.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="conference">
                  <head>The third Conference like the former.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>The</hi> 3. <hi>Solil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BEliev.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I perceive that now thou art quite chang'd, O my
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:33158:88"/>Soul; For whereas in forme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> times thou haſt been much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted, now thou art very calm and quiet, or rather ſecure.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> So I am.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> How comes this to paſs?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> I have felt ſo much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort lately, as that upon it I did even joy too much, and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed my ſelf too much peace and tranquility, which cauſed me to ſeek out for humane Conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Contentments, at laſt; as being too inordinately diſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to live comfortably ſtill, whereas I ſhould rather have fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my ſelf for new
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Quouiam tranſibit hora illa &amp; ſequetur tentati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. Tho. a Kempis de imit. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fli.</hi> l. 2. c. 9.</note> tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; this, as now I ſee, is the cauſe of my ſecurity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> So it is, and therefore rowze up thy ſelf, O my Soul, and look about thee. For nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Satan is aſleep, nor the fleſh quite dead; but both are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on with renewed ſtrength, and
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:33158:88"/>therefore we muſt reſiſt them by faith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> How by faith?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> In this caſe of ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I ſee no fitter weapon to be uſed by faith, than the ſight and ſerious conſideration of helliſh torments, compared with Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly joyes, that ſo being afraid of the one, and inflamed with a deſire of the other, thou mayeſt reſiſt Satan, and avoid ſin, unto which now thou art more prone than thou haſt been in times paſt; for ſecurity brings Licenciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and much imbecility.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> I like this well, and therefore make choice of one apt Subject or other whereon I may now muſe and meditate.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> Me thinks that fearful place in <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.51. againſt Hypocrites, whoſe portion ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth, will in this thy caſe be very ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable.</p>
                  <pb n="168" facs="tcp:33158:89"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> So it will be, for one may well ſuſpect himſelf to be but an Hypocrite when he is ſo ſecure; as I am now, being apt to yeild to any temptation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> Mark then, O my Soul, the two Principal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Hell here: in extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guible heat, and intollerable cold, for of
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Aug. de Tripl. habit.</hi> l. c. 2.</note> heat comes weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, of cold gnaſhing of teeth, whence reſult innumerous ſorts of puniſhments to be endured in that ſiery lake, even intollerable thirſt, the puniſhment of hunger, the puniſhment of horror, the puniſhment of fear, the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of anguiſh; add dolor with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out remedies, bonds without any ſolution, vengeance without end; all which grievous Puniſhments do accompany the two foreſaid principles, with whom compare, O my Soul, the joyes of Heaven, and whatſoever<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> accompanies
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:33158:89"/>them,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> conſidering how in that bliſsful place there is ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſuch weeping, and gnaſhing of teeth, but fulneſs of. light and peace, and charity, and joy, and glory, and ſweetneſs, and melody, and
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi nulla moleſtia inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etat ſed peren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis laetitia regnat. Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> de Confl. vit. &amp; Virt. fo.</hi> 115.</note> 
                     <hi>Perenna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> beatitude, and of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ineffable good thing, which neither can be uttered, nor ever entered into the heart of man, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. whereas Hell is all full of whatſoever is contrary to ſuch bleſſedneſs.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Again conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how there are none but holy and juſt Citizens both men and Angels, whoſe King is God all powerful; whereas in Hell the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens are evil men and Angels, whoſe Prince is the chief of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils: Moreover,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> in Heaven the juſt are ſatiated and filled with the viſion of Saints and Angels, and
<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 21.21, 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> ſtreets of Gold, and gates of Pearls and Diadems of glory, and light unapproachable, and of
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:33158:90"/>
                     <hi>Jehovah</hi>'s face it ſelf above all, bleſſed for ever; whereas in Hell the damned are and ſhall be cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciated with the ſight of damned men, and Spirits, and of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil himſelf the Prince of Hell. Yea,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> conſider, how there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that may be deſired but will be found there: whereas in Hell there is not to be found ſo much as a drop of water to cool ones tongue in that mercileſs flame,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 16.24. In a word, there is nothing to be found in Heaven, but what may oblect and pleaſe; whereas in that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernal pit, there is nothing elſe but whatſoever may vex, grieve, diſpleaſe, terrifie, offend, ſting, tear, diſquiet, moleſt, afflict, and that for ever and ever, <hi>for their worm dieth not, and their fire ſhall not be quenched, Mark</hi> 9. where the ſame puniſhment is twice mentioned by Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:33158:90"/>
                     <hi>v.</hi> 44. 46. becauſe men had need be put in mind of it much and often: and therefore think on both theſe contrary habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſeriouſly, O my ſoul, and compare them exactly, and ſee what cauſe thou haſt to avoid ſin and Satan, that thou mayeſt not be caſt into that fearful lake, but rather tranſported in the arms of Angels into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, where there is only reſt and no labour, eaſe and no trouble, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility and no hoſtility, comfort and no diſcomfort, triumphing and no fighting, rejoycing and no crying, <hi>for the former things will be all paſſed away, Revel.</hi> 21.4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> O the good which you have done unto me, carrying me both into Hell and Heaven with ſuch ſeaſonable conſiderations, that I might ſee, as it were, both places; for now I do even nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeat
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:33158:91"/>ſeat and loath the worlds moſt delicious pleaſures, and richeſt treaſures, and ſtatelieſt pomp, nor do I fear much the moſt ſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingſt croſſes and troubles, that may befall me in this world; I ſee Hell is more grievous than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny torment, yea, all torments, if they were all put together; and that the profits and pleaſures of this world, though never ſo great and delectable, cannot do me ſo much good, and bring me ſo much content, and ſatisfaction, as the puniſhments of Hell, which one ſhall incur, if he yield to ſin and Satan will do hurt, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce diſcontent, anguiſh, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and vexation for ever and ever to endure, I ſee likewiſe that there is more paſſing joy, pleaſure, delight, comfort, and glory to be found in Heaven, than in any fools Paradiſe upon earth, I mean in any dainty fare
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:33158:91"/>love of women, fine cloaths, mens applauſe, abundance of wealth, flowing in with the confluence of all earthly happineſs; for there I ſee are pleaſures without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, dignity without fear, honour without envy, riches with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out loſs, abundance without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny defects, proſperity without adverſity, and eternity without vanity; yea, there is nothing but perfect love, perfect joy, perfect peace,
<note n="*" place="margin">Thoſe that have imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the earth to turn about, and the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens to ſtand ſtill, have yet ſuppoſed that we may ſtand or fit ſtill, on that whirling globe of earth: how much more may we be perſwaded of our perfect reſt above thoſe moving ſphears? <hi>Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> in his 13. <hi>Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſ. Med.</hi>
                     </note> perfect reſt: whereas here is all imperfect, in a word, there is no other voice to be heard but of triumphers and fingers, ſinging the ſweet ſongs of Sion, and of harpers having the harps of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.2. And O that I might be ſo happy as to hear ſome of thoſe ſweet ſongs that are ſung to the honour of the bleſſed trinity by thoſe heavenly Quiriſters. Well, I hope that in Gods good time I ſhall not only hear them, being
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:33158:92"/>taken up among them, upon the deſolution of this my tabernacle the body, but alſo ſhall ſing with them the ſweet ſongs of Zion to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, my dear love, and ſweet Saviour, who was ſlain for me, and redeemed me with his blood, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9. Therefore farewel all the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Quapropter recedat am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r praeſentis ſaecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li, in qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus ita naſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur at non mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riatur, &amp; ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedat amor fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turt ſaeculi, in quo ſic omnes vivificantur, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t deinceps non moriantur, &amp;c. Leo de. Conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. Vit. &amp; Virt. mihi, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o.</hi> 115.</note> world, farewel pleaſures, I am for him who hath provided for me more delicious and laſting pleaſures, even for evermore, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.11. farewel profits that may be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, I am for him who hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mifed me in Heaven a better and an induring ſubſtance, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.34. farewel all vain and glittering glory of this world, for I am for another world, where there is ordained for me a far more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding and eternal weight of glory, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. and where the glorious body of my dear love Chriſt ſhines with unconceivable
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:33158:92"/>ſplendor above the brightneſs of the Sun for ever and ever.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="conference">
                  <head>The fourth Conference. Wherein faith maketh uſe of the Word of Promiſe, touching the enjoying of God, and of the ſacred words extenuation of all wordly things.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BEliev.</hi> Why doeſt thou trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thy ſelf ſo about the things of this life, O my Soul? knoweſt thou not that all is Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? Pleaſures Vanity? Riches Vanity? Honours Vanity?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> You do well, that you mind me of it. For I am apt to forget it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but what if this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration do not, nor can take me off from the love of thoſe vain things, what ſhall I do then?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> Then elevate thy ſelf
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:33158:93"/>by faith, from viſibles and flie hence like an Eagle, and ceaſe not to mount us higher and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſtill, till thou come to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible God, who only can, muſt and will ſatiate thine (elſe) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfiable deſire, and enſoul thy ſelf, as it were, in God, who is only good, and in whom are all goods; O my Soul, excite thy ſelf and lift up all thy underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and conſider as much as thou art able, what, &amp; how great that good is, which is God: as for inſtance; all good things are delectable: conſider intenſively, how pleaſant that good muſt needs be, which comprizeth the jucundity, and pleaſantneſs of all things. Again, if that life, which is created, is ſo good, how good is then the life creating? if Salvation wrought be ſweet; how ſweet and delicious is Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation it ſelf, which worketh
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:33158:93"/>all Salvation? if wiſdome be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable, when we do but think on things created, how amiable is that wiſdom which produced all things of nothing? Laſtly if many and great delights be in things delectable, and pleaſant, what, and how much delectation muſt needs be in him, who made all things ſo delightful? And therefore why doeſt thou range ſo here, and there, O my Soul, to find out what may do thee good, among things created, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſatisfie thee? poſſeſs thy ſelf of God, in whom is every good thing, and let him fill thee, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that which is only good, and then thou ſhalt have enough, and deſire no more; for in that good, which is God, thou ſhalt find far greater joy, greater delight, grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter profit, greater glory, than all the world can poſſibly yeild thee.</p>
                  <pb n="178" facs="tcp:33158:94"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> I do not only believe it, that I ſhall find it ſo; but I do partly find it already, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, O my ſweet and gracious God, who art only good, turn thou all ſinful joy and carnal pleaſure into gall and betterneſs in me, that nothing may be ſo ſweet, dear, pleaſant, and amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unto me, as my Lord and my God, who art ſweetneſs, pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and amiableneſs it ſelf, and be thou my joy, who haſt alſo promiſed to be my reward, I humbly pray thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="conference">
                  <head>The fifth Conference. Wherein Chriſt's aid is implored againſt Satans temptations, in a time of deſertion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BEliev.</hi> I perceive, O my Soul, that thou canſt not be long quiet; for thou beginneſt to be as turbulent as ever thou haſt been.</p>
                  <pb n="179" facs="tcp:33158:94"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> So I am, and I cannot be otherwiſe diſpoſed now.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> Why ſo?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> Becauſe, he that ſhould comfort and ſuſtain me is far from me, and the tempter, whom I wiſh farther off, is nigh me, &amp; raiſes ſuch ſtorms againſt me, as that I know not what to do, that he may not ſink me. For I am like that little ſhip, <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.24. covered with the impetuous waves of his tempeſtuous, and grievious temptations beating upon me, without any ceſſation, or intermiſſion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> Let not, this diſmay thee, O my Soul, for thus Chriſt is wont to trie his beſt
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Nunquam in veni ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quem tam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligioſum &amp; devotum, qui non habuerit interdum gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae ſubtractio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</hi> Tho. a Kempis de imit. <hi>Chr.</hi> l. 2. c. 9.</note> beloved Soldiers, withdrawing himſelf from them, for a ſeaſon, that they may both ſee what need they have of him, and what they are without him, even
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde fit il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud quod cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationes bonae &amp; carae Deo placentes men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem veluti de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiant.</hi> Baſil. in Reg. brev. inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rog. 80.</note> barren, dead, and dull, unable to do any thing,
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:33158:95"/>and that they may likewiſe ſeek him the more thirſtingly, who ſeeks them even by ſuch deſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons moſt lovingly; and therefore, wreſtle thou with him, O my Soul, this being not a
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Gregor. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> ſign of reprobation but only of probati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; thy beloved hath ſufferd thee a great while, ſuffer thou alſo, and ſuſtain thy beloved, and withall ſeek him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> O ſweet love, dear Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, where art thou that thou ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteſt thy ſelf ſo long from me? when wilt thou return again un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me? O my Lord, and my God,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Bern. Serm.</hi> 54.</note> careſt, thou not that I periſh? Lo, Satan that grand adverſary of mine ſeeketh to ſink me in a
<note n="*" place="margin">Mark. 8.38.</note> ſea of miſery, O ſave me for thy names ſake.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>In mari tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulente verſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, &amp;c, Aug. Saliloq. c.</hi> 35.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Why art thou ſo fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, O thou Chriſtian Soul, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving but little faith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.26. Believe only that I can, and will
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:33158:95"/>ſave thee, and all will be well with thee, <hi>for all things are poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unto him that believeth, Mar.</hi> 9.23.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> I believe Lord, help thou mine unbelief.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Then be ſafe, and let Satan ceaſe to make a noiſe and raiſe tempeſts,
<note n="*" place="margin">Ma. 54.11.</note> that this poor ſoul toſſed with tempeſts may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and ſweetly comforted.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> Oh the eaſe! and oh the peace and joy that I feel and find in thee and by thee, ſweet Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our! o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> what a mighty Chriſt is this my Chriſt, that even Satan that ſtrong man himſelf muſt and doth obey him!</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="conference">
                  <head>The ſixth Conference: Wherein uſe is made of Chriſt's incarnation by faith againſt ſin.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BEliev.</hi> how doſt thou now, O my Soul?</p>
                  <pb n="182" facs="tcp:33158:96"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> I ſhould do well enough were it not for ſin that abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable thing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> We may not expect an abſolute perfection here, ſin will ever
<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 12.1.</note> cleave even to God's dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt children, as long as they live, and therefore let not that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>may thee.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> If one did not give way to it, it would not trouble me ſo, but now I cannot but be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and much perplexed, being conſcious of too much yielding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and complying.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> Though this be an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy caſe, yet pray and truſt in God, O my ſoul, who will not therefore withdraw his mercies from thee, nor forſake thee, but rather aſſiſt thee for after times, ſo that ſin which is ſuch a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous burden unto thee, ſhall be diminiſhed &amp; demoliſhed in thee more and more, that it may not
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:33158:96"/>reign over thee, <hi>Rom,</hi> 6.14.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> I fear that I have even ſo wearied God with ſin that he will not hear me, though I ſhould make never ſo many prayers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I am ſo full of ſin, for ſo it is written, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.15. <hi>When you make many prayers, yet I'le not hear you, your hands are full of blood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> What a ſtrange com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint is this that I hear! where is thy faith, O my Chriſtian ſoul, that thou makeſt ſuch a fearful concluſion? God ſpeaks there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt irrepentant ſinners, who lay nothing to heart, and revolt more and more, v. 3.5. but thou on the contrary art not only ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of fin, and the danger of it, but alſo ſtriveſt againſt it more and more, and therefore that place concerns not thee; ſo as that thou may eſt boldly come to the Throne of grace in the time
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:33158:97"/>of need,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Si forte ex humana infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate labi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur non ideo deſperemus, ſed iterum recur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramus ad cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentem medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, &amp;c. Bern. in Scala pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rad. c.</hi> 12.</note> notwithſtanding thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thy ſad condition, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.16.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> Do you ſay ſo? the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> I'le adventure it again, and ſay with the good
<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 15.22, 23, 24, 25, 26.</note> woman of <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> have mercy on me, O Lord, thou Son of <hi>David,</hi> for I am grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly vexed with the Devil.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt.</hi> I am not ſent to be a Saviour, but to thoſe that obey me, who alſo may only expect ſalvation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.9. but thou haſt been diſobedient and rebellious againſt me.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> Yet Lord help me.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt. It is not meet to take the childrens bread, and to caſt it to dogs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul. Truth Lord, yet the dogs eat of the erumbs which fall from their maſters table,</hi> therefore if I may not obtain ſo much mercy and grace as others, who have been more obedient and dutiful than I, who am like a dog retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:33158:97"/>to his vomit, in that I have recommitted ſo many ſins, which I ſhould have omitted, yet let me find but ſome crumbs of mercy, crumbs are not denyed to dogs; and that I may not be ſuch a dog, returning to my former diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, help me, I pray thee, and ſave me from ſin, for therefore thou cameſt into the world, that thou mayeſt ſave ſinners, of whom I a poor ſinful ſoul am chief.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt.</hi> O dear Soul, great is thy Faith, be it unto thee even as thou wilt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> Oh the comfort! and oh the quietneſs, and tranquility, which I find in thee and by thee, ſweet Saviour! for now I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that neither Satan nor ſin ſhall prevail againſt me, to ſeparate me from my dear love Chriſt, who ſaves me from evils paſt, fuſcitates and raiſes me from the preſent, and fortifieth me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:33158:98"/>thoſe which are to come. O Lord Jeſus, if thou didſt not thus preſerve me, there is no ſin in the world which I might not, commit againſt thee; for I know that there is no evil perpetrated and done by any man, which may not alſo be acted by another man, if the Creator be wanting who made man.</p>
                  <p>But now thou haſt done that for me, which hath kept me that I might not do what I would have done againſt thee; and that I might abſtain, thou dideſt prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit me; and that I might believe, thou didſt infuſe grace into me; unto thee therefore be all honour and glory.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="conference">
                  <pb n="187" facs="tcp:33158:98"/>
                  <head>The ſeventh Conference: Wherein the troubled believing Soul maketh uſe of Chriſt's death, to work the death of ſin, and promiſes to be more thankefull.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BEliev.</hi> How is it with thee now, O my ſoul?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> Not very well.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> Not well?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> No.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> Why ſo?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> I am not ſo well com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted as I have been in times paſt, and ſin begins to gather ſtrength, and I am not able to maſter it, as I do deſire.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> It may be thou haſt drawn this miſery upon thy ſelf by not being
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Tho. à Kem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> pis de Imit. Chr. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note> thankful enough for mercies &amp; comforts formerly diſtilled upon thee, or by ſome
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:33158:99"/>ſecret pride, which if it be ſo, the cauſe muſt be firſt removed, then Faith muſt be rightly uſed, and all will be well.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> You have ſpoken as right as may be, I am ſuch an unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful creature, and ſo high ſpirited by nature, and therefore it is juſt with God to bereave me both of comforts and ſtrength to reſiſt the common Adverſary, who go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and goeth continually, ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whom he may davour, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8. and whom by no other means I ſhall be able to reſiſt, but only by Faith; and therefore I promiſe both to be more grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, for the future by God's help, and alſo more humble and lowly denying my ſelf in all things, and aforibing all honour and glory unto him, of whom are all things, yea,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Sileat ſibi &amp; ipſa anima &amp; tranſeat ſe mon cogit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ndo ſe, ſed de te Deus mous, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> &amp;c. Aug. Man, c.</hi> 12.</note> paſſing by my ſelf, ſo in my thoughts as that I may not think of my ſelf but of God, who is
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:33158:99"/>my only hope and confidence; and that I may overcome for the future both ſin and Satan, who is the Author of ſin; I'le, by the grace of God, ſet faith a work, &amp; eye eſpecially the bitter
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Nullum tam potens eſt tam efficax contra ardorem libi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinis medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum, quam mors redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toris mei.</hi> Id. cap. 23.</note> death &amp; paſſion of my dear Saviour, <hi>who loved me and gave himſelf for me,</hi> that he might mundify me, &amp; redeem me from
<note n="*" place="margin">Tit. 2.14.</note> all iniquity, perſwading my ſelf, that I ſhall be delivered in his own good time even from theſe ſinful luſts and paſſions, which now do ſo moleſt me; yea, I'le alſo call upon him even now forthwith, deſiring his heavenly highneſs, that he will by the power of his death work the death of my ſins, and free me from Satans power and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> Well ſaid, this is the courſe thou muſt take, O my ſoul, and therefore call thou up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lord in this time of need,
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:33158:100"/>for he hath ſaid, <hi>Call upon me in the day of trouble, I'le deliver thee, and thou ſhalt glorifie me, Pſal.</hi> 50.15. Mark this golden ſentence, O my ſoul, for here is both a Precept for thee, to bind thee, and a promiſe to aſſure thee, the Precept is <hi>call upon me,</hi> yea,
<note place="margin"> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> Clama.</note> cry unto me and ſpare not, as if thou durſt not ſpeak, being afraid, but rather lift up thy voice and cry aloud, as being commanded to be ſo bold; the Promiſe is, <hi>and I will deliver thee,</hi> or I'le looſe thee from thy bonds, for ſo much the original
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> imports, even a ſolution from bonds; for troubles are as bonds, and ſo are ſins, <hi>and thou ſhalt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify me;</hi> note how the Lord doth here promiſe not only to free thee from troubles, but alſo to cauſe thee to glorify him, being freed out of troubles, as which of thy ſelf thou canſt not do, though
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:33158:100"/>but even now thou didſt promiſe and vow to do it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> Are not theſe thy words, O my Lord, my God, who muſt help me? didſt not thou dictate them into <hi>David's</hi> pen, and leave them recorded in thy book, even for me, to excite and to ſecure me? Lo, I am in trouble, O Lord, being faſt bound and capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated, as it were, of ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.23. and I cannot unite my ſelf, of my ſelf; but thou canſt, who art omnipotency it ſelf, and therefore I call even to thee, to help me. For thou haſt ſaid, call upon me in the day of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and I aſſure my ſelf that thou wilt not leave me, becauſe thou haſt promiſed me, that thou wilt deliver me, ſaying, I will deliver, or looſe thee. Looſe me therefore, O thou, who art moſt free, and unbounded and yet bound to free me, having
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:33158:101"/>bound thy ſelf by a promiſe, to ſuccor me, O let not ſin, let not Satan keep me bound, whom thou Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> haſt redeemed by thy precious blood, but free me, O free me, by thy power, from the power of the one, and tyranny of the other, that I may freely ſerve thee; being comforted in thee. Yea, Lord, when thou haſt enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged me, then enable me alſo and cauſe me to glory fie thee. For thou haſt promiſed that alſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, ſaying, and thou ſhalt glory fie me, taking that ſaying to be a promiſe, as well as a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept. For elſe if thou ſhouldſt but command me that I muſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fie thee, and ſhouldſt not alſo cauſe me to do what thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeſt, I ſhould never be able to do what I ought, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently thou ſhouldeſt never have the glory, which is due to thy holy name. And therefore
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:33158:101"/>bleſſed be thy holy name, O my God, and Saviour, who in one word haſt both injoyned, and promiſed me that I ſhall glorifie thee. O inexhauſtible Fountain of all grace and glory, cauſe me therefore to glorifie thee, and to be grateful unto thee, for every mercy that I do or ſhall receive of thee, and ſuffer me not to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get either it, or my ſelf, and to ſeek my ſelf and mine own glory in any thing I do, or ſhall do for thee, I humbly and ardently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="conference">
                  <head>The eighth Conference. Wherein the believing Soul maketh uſe of Chriſts overcoming of the world againſt the world.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BEliev.</hi> O Lord my God, who, being the eternal Son of the eternal God, haſt given thy ſelf
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:33158:102"/>for me, to deliver me, a ſervant, and waſt made man, that I, a man, might be made a child of God, being free from ſin, which dwells in every man, <hi>Ro.</hi> 7.20. (thee, God and man, exempted) who art only without ſin, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.15. Yea, didſt therefore over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come it in thee, who art God and man, <hi>John.</hi> 16.33. deliver me, I pray thee, from ſin, even from this <hi>Luciferian</hi> pride, feral paſſion, and this Soul-waſting envy, and ſelf deſtroying ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>love, and from this evil cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, and from theſe unruly luſts.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt. <hi>Doſt thou not believe that I am able to do it? Mat.</hi> 9.28, 29.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> Yea, Lord,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Then according to thy faith be it unto thee;</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> O my moſt ſweet and bleſſed Saviour, how great is thy mercy! For when I ſilly wretch
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:33158:102"/>did but call, thou didſt hear me by and by, and when I was in fight, thou didſt corrobrate me, and when I was ready to ſink, thou didſt ſupport and ſuſtain me, and when I did even deſpair in my ſelf, thou didſt lift me up above my ſelf. Bleſſed be thy holy name for thy great and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable mercy.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="conference">
                  <head>The ninth Conference. Wherein the believing Soul maketh uſe of the love of Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſin.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>SOul.</hi> O thou Heavenly fire, which alwaies ſhineſt, and O my dear love, which alwaies bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, ſhine I pray thee from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven into me, and inflame me with thy great love, ſo as that nothing in this world may be ſo dear un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, as thou my dear Saviour,
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:33158:103"/>yea, let the world it ſelf be as dead unto me, as it was to thy ſervant <hi>Paul,</hi> who now liveth and ſhines with thee in glory, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.14. and do thou, which art life it ſelf, live in me as thou liveſt in him, that I alſo may live in thee with him, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt.
<note n="*" place="margin">Cant. 2.14.</note> 
                     <hi>O my dove, thou art thus in the clefts of the Rock,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in me, who am thy Rock, and deſireſt nothing more than me; be of good cheer, for thou ſhalt both love me more than e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thou didſt, and I'le expreſs my love toward thee more than ever I did, and I will ſo ſtupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thy ſenſes within thee, as that the world ſhall be as crucified un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, and I'le even live in thee, and work mightily by thee, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.29. and thou ſhalt live in me, and with me here and hereafter eternally, <hi>John</hi> 6.56.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> O how ſweet, how ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhing,
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:33158:103"/>and how comfortable are theſe words which I hear, ſweet Jeſus! more to be deſired are they than Gold, yea, than much fine gold, ſweeter alſo than the honey and the honey-comb, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.10. for, by them thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant is now aſſured, that the world ſhall be ſubdued in me, &amp; that thou alſo thy ſelf, my moſt glorious Redeemer, wilt be my exceeding great and all-ſufficient reward, living in me and with me now and eternally: O that this love and good affection, which thou, O my Love, haſt diffuſed in me, might now be like that holy fire, which in the time of the Law was to burn alwaies, and never to go out upon thine Altar, and that no waters of affliction might quench it, and that no flouds of Satannical temptations drown it, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.7. O do thou, who art Love it ſelf, alwaies pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:33158:104"/>it, that it may ever burn and never go out, I humbly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate and pray thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="conference">
                  <head>The tenth Conference. Wherein the believing Soul mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth uſe of Chriſts interceſſion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BEliev.</hi> O my Soul, as thou haſt done in times paſt, ſo ceaſe not now to invocate thy dear Saviour, that he will ſave thee more and more foom thy ſins. <hi>For he is thy Lord, and therefore worſhip thou him, Pſal.</hi> 45.11.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> So I will by Gods help, O moſt fair, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.2. Moſt holy, moſt gracious, moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful Saviour, intercede for me, that I may be kept from this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil world, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.34.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt.</hi> I have prayed for thee, <hi>John</hi> 17.25. and I even
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:33158:104"/>
                     <hi>ever live to make interceſſion for thee, Hebr.</hi> 7.25. wherefore doubt not, but aſſure thy ſelf for certain, that thou ſhalt be kept from the evil which thou feareſt, and overcome the world which thou hateſt; for he that is my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and my God, is alſo thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and thy God, <hi>John</hi> 20.17. and I know that he heareth me alwaies, <hi>John</hi> 11.42. and there fore hath heard me in this thing alſo, that I have prayed for, when I deſired him to keep thee from the evil, <hi>John</hi> 17.15.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> I doubt not but God thy Father and my Father hath heard thee interceding for me, and me praying for my ſelf for thy ſake, and will hear me, for thou haſt ſaid, <hi>whatſoever ye ſhall ask the Father in my name, he will give it unto you, John</hi> 16.23. O ſweet name! how pleaſant? how de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectable? how amiable? and how
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:33158:105"/>prevalent therefore muſt thou needs be in the mouth of him that prayeth, and in the ears of him that heareth ſuch prayers, as are ſo ſweetned with thy ſweet ſavour, as with oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment poured forth? <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.3. O bleſſed be thy ſweet &amp; holy name, ſweet Jeſus, in the which thou cauſeſt me to truſt by this thy ſweet and precious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="conference">
                  <head>The eleventh Conference. Wherein the troubled believing Soul maketh uſe of Chriſt's Prophetical Office.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BEliev.</hi> It ſhould ſeem that thou art not yet, nor canſt be altogether quiet.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> Quiet? No, No, as long as I have this body of ſin about me, I do not look for it.</p>
                  <pb n="201" facs="tcp:33158:105"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> But yet thou muſt not be ſo much diſquieted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> Dejected? how can I chuſe, ſeeing that God is ſtill ſo much by me offended?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> But this is not the way to peace which thou goeſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> Which way then would you have me to go?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> That way which is the beſt way.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> The beſt way? which is the beſt way?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> Chriſt who hath ſaid of himſelf, that he is the way it ſelf, <hi>John</hi> 14.6.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> You ſay true, and I had almoſt forgotten my ſelf, forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the way it ſelf, and pleaſing my ſelf with grief and ſorrow for my ſins, which though it be good and laudable when it is mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and ſeaſonable, leading the penſive and perplexed ſinner to
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:33158:106"/>Chriſt, yet is it not ſufficient, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailable when it goeth alone, and is ſeparated from Chriſt; for he it is who muſt perfume &amp; ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten all ſuch tears and ſorrows as ſhall be unto God acceptable; he muſt free us alſo from ſin, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which freedom no grief for ſins paſt can be profitable.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> Then go to Chriſt, O my ſoul, having been eſtranged from him, by reaſon of ſin, which cauſed thee to abſent thy ſelf from him being ſo dejected, and to count thy ſelf unworthy of him, being ſo polluted.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> So I will by Gods help, only adviſe me what I ſhall ſay unto him, when I come before him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> Urge him upon his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetical Office, by vertue where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he is bound to turn thee from iniquities, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.26.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> O thou great Prophet,
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:33158:106"/>and heavenly Doctor, who, being come from
<note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 3.2.</note> God, God of God, light of light, teacheſt what no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Rabby can teach, &amp; canſt do what no man elſe can do, even turn men from their iniquities; O turn me alſo from mine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, and ſave me from my ſins; and let not ſo many leſſons thought by thy Servants, who are but men, be loſt in me, that look beyond them unto thee, who art both God and man, ordained by God to turn man from ſin, which is the greateſt folly, he being the greateſt and wiſeſt Doctor, yea, Wiſdom it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt.</hi> I perceive, O Chriſtian ſoul, that needs thou wilt be taught of God, without whoſe teaching the Doctrines and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions of men are all in vain;
<note place="margin">Cor. 3.7.</note> and I ſee that thou groundeſt thy requeſt upon a ſure and everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Rock, even upon the Word
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:33158:107"/>of truth
<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.23.</note> which abideth for ever, and cannot be denied; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as I have ſaid, that <hi>he who cometh unto me ſhall in no wiſe be caſt out, John</hi> 6.37. So be ſure that I will not reject thee, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who ſo comeſt unto me to
<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 11.29.</note> learn of me, who am ſent to
<note n="*" place="margin">Deut. 18.15.</note> turn thee from thine iniquities more and more, that they may not have dominion over thee.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> I am perſwaded, that thou wilt do even as thou haſt ſaid, Lord Jeſus; for it's impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that God ſhould lie. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.18. and therefore I will even reſt on thee, and put my whole truſt and affiance in thee, for my turning from mine iniquities, caſting away all ſelf confidence, and ſelf-relying on an arm of fleſh; for, in vain is the help of man without thee, who madeſt man, and cauſeſt me alſo at this time
<note n="*" place="margin">Pſ. 119.49.</note> to truſt in thee, and to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim
<note n="*" place="margin">Acts 3.26.</note>
                     <pb n="205" facs="tcp:33158:107"/>all power and abilitie in man to ſave, and to
<note place="margin">Jer. 31.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> turn himſelf or any other man.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="conference">
                  <head>The Twelfth Conference. Wherein the believing ſoul makes uſe of Chriſt's Kingly Office againſt ſin.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BEliev.</hi> O King of Kings and Lord of Lords, I that am moſt poor, come to thee that art moſt rich <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> I, being moſt miſerable, come to thee that art moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful; being moſt weak, to thee that art moſt ſtrong; and being moſt ſinful, to thee that art moſt holy and good, deſiring thee, that of thine infinite mercie thou wilt deliver me out of my miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and according to thy power, ſubdue the ſtrength and potency of Satans tyranny; and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the vertue of thy Kingly
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:33158:108"/>Office, wilt debilitate &amp; weaken the force and power of ſin, that it may not reign.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Doſt thou believe that I am ſuch a King indeed? and thy King, who not only can, but alſo will ſubdue thy ſins?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> I do believe it, and therefore, O my King, and my God,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 84.4.</note> rule thou in my heart, even in the midſt of thine and mine enemies, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.2. and ſo rule, as that my Soul may rule my Bodie, Reaſon my Soul, Grace Reaſon, and I my whole ſelf may be wholly and ſolely ſubject to thy holy will it ſelf, both inwardly and outwardly, and that eternally: O Lord, thou haſt ſaid, <hi>Ask and ye ſhall have, Luke</hi> 11.9. <hi>I</hi> aſk, help, let me have it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Thou ſhalt have it, &amp; muſt have it; for <hi>I</hi> am ſo tied by the Promiſe which <hi>I</hi> have made,
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:33158:108"/>as that <hi>I</hi> cannot denie thee, what ever thou doſt requeſt me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>I</hi> have ſaid, that <hi>every one that asketh receiveth, and he that ſeeketh findeth, and to him that knocketh it ſhall be opened, Luke</hi> 11.10.</p>
                  <p>Believ. <hi>I will extoll thee, my God, O King, and I will bleſs thy N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap> for ever and ever:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 45.1, 2.</note> eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day will I bleſs thee, and I will praiſe thy Name for ever and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, for thou haſt heard me, and art become my ſalvation, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my mouth ſhall ſpeak the prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the Lord, and let all fleſh bleſs his holy Name for ever and ever,</hi> Pſal. 145.21.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="conference">
                  <pb n="208" facs="tcp:33158:109"/>
                  <head>The Thirteenth Conference. Wherein the believing ſoul returns from the vain things of the world to Chriſt, and maketh uſe of the ſacred words precepts to reſiſt ſin, craving aſſiſtance of Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BEliev.</hi> O my Soul, why doſt thou range ſo, and wandereſt here and there, whereas here is not thy reſt?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> You do well to recall me, for I am apt to go aſtray, like a loſt ſheep, and to forget both God and my ſelf, and to mind the vain things of this vile world.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> So thou art, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing thou art thus ſenſible of it, <hi>return unto thy reſt, O my Soul, Pſal.</hi> 116.7. and flie thou hence, like a Dove, even like
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:33158:109"/>
                     <hi>Noah's</hi> dove, which finding no reſt any where for the ſole of her foot, returned into the Ark flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting upon the waters, <hi>Gen.</hi> 8.6. ſo do thou return from fleeing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad unto Jeſus Chriſt typified by that Ark, who hath promiſed thee reſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> You ſay right, ſo I ought to do, and therefore I will ſeek no farther abroad, nor think ſo much upon ſuch vain and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory things as I have done, but rather come back again to him who doth ſo lovingly invite me, ſaying, <hi>Return, return, O Shula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite, return return,</hi> and I will ſay unto him
<note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 15.18.</note> 
                     <hi>I have ſinned againſt Heaven and againſt thee, and am no more worthy to be called thy Spouſe:</hi> but thou canſt cure me, as well as call me, and make me as clean, as ever was any belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Soul, and therefore <hi>Take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all mine iniquities and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:33158:110"/>me graciouſly, Hoſ.</hi> 14.2.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt.</hi> I will do it, only ſin no more, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.14. and be not ſo worldly, and ſo vain hereafter, as thou haſt been in times paſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> I hope I ſhall never be ſo overtaken again, only do thou
<note n="*" place="margin">Jer. 31.</note> turn me, and I ſhall be turned, and ſubdue ſin in me as thou haſt promiſed me, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.26. <hi>Mic.</hi> 7.19. &amp; keep home my thoughts and fix them upon thy ſelf, and then <hi>I</hi> cannot poſſibly be ſo wordly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt.</hi> I ſee thou wilt needs hold me faſt by my word, and I cannot go from it, becauſe I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny my ſelf, being the truth it ſelf, and therefore
<note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 7.50.</note> 
                     <hi>go in peace, thy faith hath ſaved thee;</hi> for lo, I, whom by thy faith thou didſt embrace and urge by the Word of Promiſe, which I have ſpoken (as <hi>I</hi> am God who cannot lye, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.18.) even I my ſelf will
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:33158:110"/>do that for thee, which thou canſt not do without me, that is, I will more and more ſubject this vile world unto thee, and abject thy worldly luſts and affections from thee, and deject the ſtrong mans holds in thee, and reject his Satanical proffers by thee, and eject even all his wicked in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections and ſuggeſtions out of thee, that they not be noxious and hurtful unto thee.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> O Lord Jeſus
<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 22.20.</note> come and do it, yea, be thou like a Roe, or young Hart upon the mountains of <hi>Bether,</hi> or of
<note n="*" place="margin">Cant. 2. <hi>ult. Nam</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>ſignificat divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionem.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>diviſion,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king haſt to fulfill thy Word in me, for lo <hi>I</hi> am even divided in two, having a will and a will, or a will which is againſt a will, a will regenerate, warring againſt the will unregenerate, and yet but one will; thus divided, as it were, in two, ſo as that
<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 5.17.</note> 
                     <hi>I</hi> cannot as <hi>I</hi> ſhould overcome this vile
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:33158:111"/>world, but mine eies are towards thee, O Lord, who only canſt &amp; muſt end this quarrel, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>I</hi> ſay with <hi>David, make haſt to help me, O Lord my ſalvation, Pſal.</hi> 37.22.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Surely <hi>I come quickly, Rev.</hi> 22.20.</p>
                  <p>Soul. <hi>Even ſo come Lord Jeſus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="conference">
                  <head>The Fourteenth Conference.</head>
                  <head type="sub">Wherein the believing Soul deſires Chriſts preſence that it may be able to overcome the world.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BEliev.</hi> Thou muſt overcome thy ſelf in many things, O my Soul, if thou wilt come to enjoy a more perfect peace, and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility, being freed from many doubts, fears, diſcomforts, and diſcontents, which many times ſurprize thee.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> Which be thoſe many
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:33158:111"/>things, wherein <hi>I</hi> muſt yet more overcome my ſelf?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> Firſt of all thou art too ſoon and too much angry, and paſſionate; yea, and thou loveſt pleaſure too well yet, even fine ſights and dainty fare, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and mens applauſe, and vain talk, and idle ſports, and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous reports; again, thou haſt not laid aſide yet thine envy, thy malice, and thy revengefulneſs, thy high mindedneſs, and ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceitedneſs, and thy ſloathful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and evil thoughts; yea, while the very ſteps of thy beſt beloved are yet hot in thee, thou doſt even intromit adulterous and moſt ignominous thoughts of pride and revenge, and luſts, and ſtrife, and worldly gain, and vain delights, and graceleſs talk; and thoſe ears, which a little before did drink in the Word ſpoken by the everliving God himſelf, are
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:33158:112"/>peſtilently infected, and thoſe eies which were even lately bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed with ſacred and precious tears, are horribly contaminated, and that heart which was recent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and newly viſited of the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial Bridegroom, is wofully ſoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and polluted, and that tongue which did decant, ſing, and ſay the praiſes and ſongs of God, pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully abuſed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> All this is moſt true, <hi>I</hi> cannot deny it, and therefore wo is me, that <hi>I</hi> have ſo loving and gracious a God, and Saviour who may now juſtly ſay unto me <hi>what could I have done more unto thee, that I have not done for thee? Iſa.</hi> 5.9. thou waſt not and <hi>I</hi> created thee, thou haſt ſinned and made thy ſelf Satans bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave and <hi>I</hi> redeemed thee, thou didſt go aſtray in the worlds cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference with the ungodly, and I elected thee from among
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:33158:112"/>them, I gave thee grace where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thou mighteſt overcome this vile world;
<note n="*" place="margin">Jer. 3.1.</note> but thou haſt played the harlot with the world, and neglected that grace and faith which I
<note n="*" place="margin">Jude v. 3.</note> delivered unto thee. Again, I would fain have made mine
<note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 14.23.</note> abode with thee conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually, and therefore I have often knocked at the door of thy heart, ſaying, <hi>open to me, my Siſter, my Love, my Dove, my undefiled, for
<note n="*" place="margin">Cant. 5.2.</note> my head is filled with the dew, and my locks with the drops of the night,</hi> by reaſon of my long waiting for thee, but thou haſt not opened unto me, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what an unhappy creature am I, that have ſo horribly and deteſtably abuſed and offended the Lord my Creator, which made me!</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Thy caſe indeed is grievous, O perplexed Soul, but yet deſpair not; for
<note n="*" place="margin">Joel. 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> the Lord
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:33158:113"/>thy <hi>God is gracious, and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and ſlow to anger, and of great kindneſs and repenteth him of the evil,</hi> and therefore he ſaith. <hi>Thou haſt played the harlot with many lovers, yet return again un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, Jer.</hi> 3.1.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> Are not theſe they words, O my Lord, and my God? did not they iſſue out of thy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred mouth? And are they not writen for my learning, that I, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven I, through patience and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the Scriptures might have hope? <hi>Ro.</hi> 15.4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chr.</hi> Yes verily: for the whole word of God is my word, and I am Gods word, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.13. Yea, God himſelf, <hi>John</hi> 1.1. who ſpake theſe words, for thine everlaſting comfort.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>S.</hi> I believe it, I believe it, ſweet <hi>Jeſus,</hi> dear Saviour, who art
<note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 20.28.</note> my Lord, and my God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though my ſins be great, yet
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:33158:113"/>will I not deſpair, nor be out of hope, having ſo great and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Saviour, who caſts away none, but thoſe that will caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way themſelves. O my dear Love, Chriſt, which ever burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt with love, and art
<note n="*" place="margin">Gregor. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianz.</note> more merciful, than I can poſſibly be ſinful, have mercy upon me therefore, and pardon all my grivous offences, and hainous tranſgreſſions, where with I have tranſgreſſed and ſinned againſt thee. Inflame me alſo with the inextinguible flame of thy love, ſo as that I may love nothing in this world more than thee, O my ſweeteſt Love and moſt merciful Redeemer, Chriſt <hi>Jeſus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jeſus.</hi> I ſee thou wilt needs have a pardon and me too, whom thou deſireſt to love more than all things, and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to enjoy above all things, and therefore as both the one
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:33158:114"/>and the other thou doſt deſire, ſo both thou ſhalt have; a pardon firſt, which may put away thy guiltineſs; and me too, as by whom thou mayeſt &amp; muſt over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come thy worldineſs, being wounded with arrowes of my love, and indued with ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſtrength and power from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, by me, in me, and for me; that the world may not, as it hath in times paſt, overcome thee.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> And wilt thou give thy ſelf unto me indeed, ſweet Lamb, dear Saviour, who alſo haſt
<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 2.20.</note> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thy ſelf for me?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Yes verily; for I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny my ſelf, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.13. being
<note n="*" place="margin">Hoſ. 11.9.</note> God, as well as man; a meer man may deny himſelf, when a woman will marry him, and have him, but I cannot do it; if the pooreſt creature that is will have me, believing on me, I cannot keep my ſelf from ſuch
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:33158:114"/>a poor Soul, but I muſt and will give my ſelf unto it, becauſe I have bound my ſelf to do it by the word of promiſe, <hi>Jo.</hi> 6.51. <hi>Jo.</hi> 14.23. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.17.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> O the joy, and O the comfort, which theſe ſweet words of thine diſtill into me, ſweet Saviour! For now I am fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that <hi>thou my beloved, art mine, &amp; that I am thine, Cant.</hi> 2.16. and that this vile world ſhal have no ſuch power over me, as it had formerly, and that nothing in this world ſhall be dearer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, than thou, my dear Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; and therefore I am even bold upon that aſſurance, which I ground upon thy word of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, to beſpeak thee in the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage and praiſe of thy dear Spouſe, ſaying, <hi>Let him kiſs me with the kiſſes of his mouth; thy love</hi> (O my love) <hi>is better than wine,</hi> Can. 1.2. <hi>Yea, my beloved
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:33158:115"/>ſhall even lie all night betwixt my breaſts,</hi> Cant. 1.13. And <hi>my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved is white and ruddy the chiefeſt among ten thouſand,</hi> Can. 5.10. O my beloved, be not far from me, (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.21.) at any time, but let thy mercy, truth, and love alwayes preſerve, guide, and accompany me, and whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thou giveſt any good thing unto me, give thy ſelf alſo, as well as other things, &amp; above all other things;
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Quoniam ſi cuncta qua fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſti mihi de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deris nam ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficit ſervo tuo niſi teipſum dederis.</hi> Aug. Man. c. 3.</note> for without thee they are all worth nothing, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if thou ſhouldſt give me all that thou haſt made, it would not, yea, could not content me, if thou ſhouldeſt not give thy ſelf withall, who madeſt all.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> I muſt needs inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt thee, O my Soul, (becauſe <hi>I</hi> ſee that thou art not ſo thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful as thou ſhouldeſt be, for this great mercy, which the Lord hath even now ſhewed toward
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:33158:115"/>thee) ſaying, <hi>bleſs the Lord, O my Soul, and forget not all his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, who forgiveth all thine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, who heals all thy diſeaſes, who redeems thy life from deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, who crowns thee with loving kindneſs and tender mercies, Pſ.</hi> 103.1, 2, 3, 4. I add who hath given himſelf in part already, and hath promiſed thee that he will impart himſelf yet more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> Well ſaid, for
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Qui gratiam Dei retinere deſiderat ſit gratus pro gratia data.</hi> Tho. à Kem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis, <hi>de imit. Chriſti l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note> whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever will retain grace, muſt be thankful for grace received, and therefore <hi>while I live will I praiſe the Lord, I will ſing praiſes unto my God while I have any being, Pſ.</hi> 146.2.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> Yea, <hi>Let every thing that hath breath praiſe the Lord. Alleluia, Pſal.</hi> 150.6.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="conference">
                  <pb n="222" facs="tcp:33158:116"/>
                  <head>The fifteenth Conference. Wherein the troubled believing Soul craves the promiſed hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Manna, that it may be the more couragious to fight the fight of Faith.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BEeliev.</hi> Why art thou ſad, O my Soul?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> How can I be merry, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſtitute of that true comfort which I was wont to find.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> Thou muſt look to the hand of God in it, who 1. doth ſo caſtigate and correct thee, for having been too jovial and vain in a carnal manner, 2. doth ſee that thou now art not fit for ſuch joy &amp; comfort, not being ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dejected; for though thou grieveſt now and then even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond meaſure, yet at other times thou art as fooliſh and outward, and careleſs and fearleſs, as if
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:33158:116"/>thou hadſt never known the practiſe of Godly ſorrow, which is ever to be renewed even day by day, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 51.3.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> All this is true, and therefore I do reſolve, that, by Gods help, I'le never be ſo vain, and outward, and fooliſhly merry, as I have been, but rather ſober, grave, moderate, awful, careful, and conſtant in the daily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of godly ſorrow.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Believ.</hi> So do, and then look for joy, and comfort in the Lord; who is ſaid <hi>to comfort ſuch as are ſo caſt down,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.6. and then forget not to uſe faith whereby thou mayeſt feed on the word of promiſe, as for inſtance, that in <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.17. <hi>To him that overcometh will I give to eat of the hidden manna,</hi> even joy unſpeakable to be found in me, who am that bread of life, that manna which came down from Heaven.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> So I purpoſe, and therefore, O thou ever-living bread of life, who feedeſt others, and yet never faileſt
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:33158:117"/>thy ſelf, nor art either diminiſhed, or conſumed; feed me alſo, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh me, and comfort me, as thou doeſt others, and haſt comforted me in time paſt, ſweet <hi>Jeſus,</hi> let me taſt but of the crums that fall from thee, and let me feel but ſome of thoſe raviſhing joyes, which I was wont to feel in thee, O Lord, my God, thy ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry name is as ſweet as hony, and thou thy ſelf art ſweetneſs it ſelf, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as <hi>Samſon</hi> found
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Jeſus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>melinore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>in aure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>melos, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>corde ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>bilus, ſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eſt &amp; Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicina, &amp;c. Bern. Serm.</hi> 15. <hi>ſuper Cant.</hi>
                     </note> hony in the dead Lion, which he flew, ſo let me find ſome ſweetneſs alſo in thee, who art that
<note n="*" place="margin">Judg. 14.8.</note> Lion of the tribe of <hi>Juda,</hi> whom the <hi>Jewes</hi> flew, yea, who is
<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 5.5.</note> riſen again, having overcome death, and is aſcended up into Heaven, from whence alſo I look for comfort and joy, to drop, and to deſcend upon me even as manna (whoſe taſt was like
<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 8.34.</note> waffers made with hony, <hi>Exo.</hi> 16.13. did come
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Scilicet miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſe. Non e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim fuit cadem cum Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na illa naturali, quae naſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur in Arabia.</hi> Danaeus <hi>Phyſ. Chriſt. tract.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 26.</note> out of Heaven, <hi>John</hi> 6.31. to fill and to feed the people of God upon earth. O Lord, dear
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:33158:117"/>Saviour, who art the very bread of God, which cometh down from Heaven, and giveſt life unto the world, <hi>John</hi> 6.33. give me, I pray thee, this hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den manna, that I believing on thee may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in thee <hi>with joy unſpeakable, and full of glory,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Thou art too greedy and too eager after comfort, which for its continued fruition thou ſhouldeſt rather expect in Heaven than from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; for now is the time of fighting, and hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter will come the time of tryumphing when the fight is ended; and therefore why doſt thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that in this world, which is reſerved for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther world? Doſt thou think to have a Heaven here, and a Heaven hereafter too, that is too much.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soul.</hi> Truth Lord, it is too much for me, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve not the leaſt of thy mercies, yet ſeeing thou haſt promiſed both Heavens, even a Heaven in Heaven and a Heaven upon earth, joy here and joy hereafter, therefore I look for both, even for a taſt now, and for full fruition hereafter, and I'le not leave thee till thou bleſs me with ſuch joy, crown me with ſuch comforts, as may refreſh, &amp; ſtrengthen, and encourage me ſo, as that like <hi>Jonathan</hi> I may with new ſupplied fortitude and valour reaſſault my ſpiritual enemies, having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted how ſweet thou art, O Lord my God, even ſweeter than that moſt ſweet and pleaſant hony which <hi>Jonathan</hi> had taſted, when his
<note n="*">1 Sam. 14.27.31</note> eies were inlightened, &amp; himſelf ſo corrobora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:33158:118"/>and enlivened, as that he was able to diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit a hoſt of men. Nor am I the firſt that crave this Heaven; for thy ſervant <hi>David,</hi> who was a man after thine own heart, did requeſt thee for the very ſame thing before me, ſaying, <hi>reſtore unto me the joy of thy Salvation, Pſal.</hi> 81.12. and therefore let not my Lord be diſpleaſed with me, who follow ſuch an approved pattern, ſaying after him, who ſaid ſo firſt, O Lord, reſtore unto me alſo the joy of thy Salvation, which I have found wanting a long time, &amp; after the ſpouſe in <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Stay me with flagons, comfort me with apples. For I am ſick of love.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt.</hi> I ſee thou wilt not be denied, and I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny my words, and therefore <hi>as one whom his mother comforteth, ſo will I comfort thee, and thou ſhalt be comforted,</hi> Iſa. 66.13.</p>
                  <p>Believ. <hi>As the Apple-tree among the trees of the wood, ſo is my Beloved among the Sons.</hi> For lo, <hi>Now I ſit down under his ſhadow with great delight, and his fruit is ſweet unto my taſt,</hi> Cant. 2.3. <hi>and therefore return unto thy reſt, O my Soul, for the Lord hath dealt bountifully with thee; and now what ſhall I render un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord for all his benefits towards me: I will take the Cup of ſalvation, and call upon the Name of the Lord, becauſe he hath inclined his ears unto me, therefore will I call upon him as long as I live,</hi> Pſal. 116.2, 3, 12, 13.</p>
                  <closer>Alleluia.</closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:33158:118"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
